<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable discourse against toleration with a preface wherein the nature of persecution in general and the unjust complaints of the dissenting parties concerning it in particular are distinctly considered.</title>
            <author>Assheton, William, 1641-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4041</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07869639</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07869639</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26073)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1194:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable discourse against toleration with a preface wherein the nature of persecution in general and the unjust complaints of the dissenting parties concerning it in particular are distinctly considered.</title>
                  <author>Assheton, William, 1641-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>26, 86, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Rumbold,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40183:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SEASONABLE DISCOURSE AGAINST TOLERATION.</p>
            <p>WITH A PREFACE, Wherein the Nature of Perſecution in general, and the unjuſt Complaints of the Diſſenting Parties concerning it in particular, are diſtinctly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Rumbold,</hi> in <hi>Butcher-hall</hi> Lane, near <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Church, 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40183:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40183:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE To the READER.</head>
            <p>THough <hi>Controverſies</hi> in Religion are (hypotheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally) <hi>neceſſary,</hi> (for ſo long as there is either Ignorance or Malice in the hearts of Men, there will be Differences in Opinion, and Animoſities amongſt them) yet a prudent well-regulated endeavour to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and aſſwage them, is a work truly <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable,</hi> however it may be fruitleſs, and unſuccesfull in the <hi>end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do indeed heartily pray for it, yet dare not (as yet) promiſe my ſelf ſo good a return of theſe my poor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as my <hi>Brethrens</hi> conviction; <hi>Prejudice</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> (from which the deareſt of Gods <hi>Children</hi> are not wholly exempted) being not ſo eaſily remov'd; The utmoſt that I can now expect, (and which I hope they will have no cauſe to deny mee) is their favourable <hi>Abſolution</hi> from that common, yet unworthy Reflection of a <hi>Temporizing For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſt;</hi> it being my unfeigned <hi>Judgment,</hi> (after a ſtrict im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall inquiry into the nature of ſuch Impoſitions) that my <hi>Subſcription</hi> to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is not only warrantable, but neceſſary.</p>
            <p>'Tis not my buſineſs at preſent, to give a particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication or defence of thoſe <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> which my <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Brethren</hi> (both in Preſs and Pulpit) have thought fit to oppoſe; That task hath been with ſo much <hi>Learning</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40183:3"/> (and withall ſo much <hi>Moderation</hi>) performed (to omit others) by thoſe two worthy Inſtruments of Gods glory, Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hoeker,</hi> that I have often (and I think not without juſt cauſe) admired, that any man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed (even) with common Abilities (ſuppoſing him of a meek and docile ſpirit) ſhould remain unſatisfyed, when he ſhall have but ſeriouſly peruſed the <hi>Incomparable</hi> writings of thoſe Pious and Learned Perſons.</p>
            <p>The truth is (be their pretences never ſo plauſible) tis to me very plaine, that many of my <hi>Brethren</hi> both decline, and dread <hi>Conviction;</hi> of which (amongſt other proofes) this which I now mention is a pregnant Inſtance.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had this ſmall <hi>Pamphlet</hi> appear'd in the <hi>World,</hi> but (as is uſuall in ſuch caſes, we being all deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of Novelties) it was generally ſought after, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, and (that I may return my <hi>Thanks</hi> for ſuch encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging <hi>Reception</hi>) not much diſcommended. However my <hi>Diſſenting Brethren</hi> (from whom I have deſerv'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acknowledgements) were not altogether ſo <hi>obliging;</hi> ſome of which (this is no Conjecture but a certain Truth) though they both knew the <hi>Authors</hi> Perſon, and had other endearments, ſufficient to have invited a much greater <hi>Favour,</hi> yet (having barely glanc'd upon the <hi>Title</hi>) very diſcourteouſly (not to ſay rudely) refus'd, even one ſingle peruſall of his humble <hi>Petition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs (though even contrary to my naturall <hi>Inclination</hi>) I was ſome little mov'd, to obſerve ſuch cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and irrational <hi>Perverſeneſs.</hi> For though there be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſmall Reaſon, that any man (in this <hi>Scribling</hi> Age) ſhould ſo little conſult either his <hi>Time</hi> or <hi>Purſe,</hi> as to think himſelf oblig'd to the peruſall of each impertinent <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet;</hi> yet that ſo <hi>ſmall</hi> a Tract, ſo <hi>inoffenſively</hi> compoſed,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40183:3"/> when <hi>preſented</hi> by the hand of a <hi>Friend,</hi> ſhould not find a more favourable <hi>Acceptance,</hi> is ſuch an <hi>Vngentle-man</hi> like thing, that had I the leaſure or deſigne to play the <hi>Satyriſt,</hi> it were no hard task methinks to explode ſo diſingenious an inſtance.</p>
            <p>But of this enough, if not (as ſome may judge) too much: Which yet is mention'd with this <hi>Deſigne,</hi> even to aſſure my <hi>Reader;</hi> That be his private <hi>Opinion</hi> what it will, (if he pleaſe to hazard ſome ſmall portion of Time in the peruſall of the following <hi>Pamphlet</hi>) he ſhall find nothing to <hi>offend</hi> him, but the <hi>Evidence</hi> of Truth, and downe-right <hi>Conviction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have one thing more to add, and that is an Objection; which being both plauſible and common, I ſhall firſt <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> (&amp; that in the Perſon of ſome <hi>Private</hi> weake Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) Secondly <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſolve</hi> with as much clearneſs as I am able.</p>
            <p>The Objection is this.</p>
            <p>There are indeed hot <hi>Diſputes</hi> about theſe <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and other Impoſitions in the Service of God: The <hi>Tongues</hi> and <hi>Pens</hi> of Learned men have for a long time been em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about them; the Arguments <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> both to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend and diſprove them, are of great weight, and ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rationall: They are indeed both ſo plauſible, that a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my rank and <hi>Quality</hi> (who not only wants the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>Education,</hi> but is alſo diverted from ſuch inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by a particular <hi>profeſsion</hi> which he is obliged to attend) may very well be perplexed how to behave himſelf: yet for my own part, I am much inclin'd to think; That theſe <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are very dangerous and unlawfull Things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that becauſe I obſerve ſo many <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Godly</hi> Divines, who rather then they will <hi>defile</hi> themſelves with ſuch <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions,</hi> have not only, <hi>ſuffered joyfully the ſpoyling of their goods,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40183:4"/> but alſo <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Impriſonments,</hi> Baniſhments, and a Thouſand other Indignities, to which a <hi>perſecuted</hi> people is uſually expoſed; which certainly ſuch <hi>prudent</hi> Perſons would never have done for a few <hi>Ceremonies</hi> (the cauſe of all this miſchief) were they ſuch <hi>innocent</hi> Things, as the <hi>Prelats,</hi> and their Agents have endeavoured to perſwade us.</p>
            <p>This is the Objection; To which I Anſwer as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>That which is ſaid in the firſt Place of their <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>piety,</hi> is not much to the purpoſe,</p>
            <p>For <hi>Firſt,</hi> ſuch pretences (being very advantageous to any <hi>Cauſe</hi> whatſoever) are far more common then true. The <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic eſt vulgus; ex veritate pauca, ex opinione multa aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat.</hi> Cic. Orat. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Vulgar ſort</hi> (who are chiefly concerned in the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection) are no competent <hi>Judges</hi> in theſe Caſes, but much leſs in the former then the latter. But Secondly, granting them to be as <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>pious,</hi> as their admiring <hi>Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes</hi> can fancy, or my <hi>Charity</hi> could wiſh them; yet we muſt remember, that the moſt <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>pious</hi> are but <hi>Men,</hi> and therefore do but <hi>know</hi> in part, and are <hi>ſanctified</hi> in part; and (as the learned <note n="b" place="margin">Pref. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Serm. Sect. 6.</note> Bp. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> expreſſeth it) <hi>By the power of Godlineſs in their Hearts are no more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from the poſſibility of falling into Error through Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, then from the poſſibility of falling into Sin through In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity;</hi> Which ſhould therefore prompt us, (as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt courſe) to guide our <hi>Actions,</hi> not by <hi>Example,</hi> which (through different Circumſtances) is various, and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but by <hi>Precept</hi> which is ſure and fixt; not to have mens <hi>Perſons</hi> in ſuch <hi>Admiration,</hi> as to embtace their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and practiſes againſt the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>Right Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> if <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> muſt paſs for <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40183:4"/> (which yet they will not, it being no good Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, ſuch a <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Pious</hi> Man, or ſuch a learned and pious <hi>Company</hi> of Men holds this <hi>Opinion,</hi> therefore 'tis true yet) I ſay if theſe muſt be urg'd for <hi>Logick</hi> (though Compariſons are harſh, and for the moſt part odious) I think it might eaſily appear (without diſparagement be it ſpoken) That there are as Honeſt, Religious, Zealous good men, that have willingly and chearfully <hi>ſubmitted</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as the beſt of them all that have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the ſame.</p>
            <p>Our Pious-Fore-fathers (to whom under God, we owe the <hi>purity</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>ſome</hi> of which embrac'd a <hi>Stake</hi>) had more moderate apprehenſions, then the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Generation.</p>
            <p>For, when the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> had forc'd them to a <hi>Separation</hi> (and that in Obedience to God, who commands us neither to believe <hi>Lies,</hi> nor to commit <hi>Sin,</hi> neither of which they could avoid by continuing in <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> with her) though they left many of her <hi>Ceremonies</hi> (the number of them being great and burthenſome) yet they thought fit to retain ſome others of them, and that for <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency</hi> in the Service of God.</p>
            <p>If it be replyed (as uſually it is) That the <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (being carried on by thoſe that were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, made of the ſame <hi>Clay,</hi> and ſubject to the like <hi>paſsions</hi> with others) was at beſt but ſmall and <hi>imperfect,</hi> it being beyond the <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of Man, either to foreſee, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all Inconveniences on a ſudden, and therefore, that it was the Duty of <hi>After-Ages,</hi> to perfect and <hi>complete</hi> what they had ſo happily <hi>begun,</hi> by removing this <hi>Rubbiſh</hi> out of the Houſe of God; To this I Anſwer,</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Topick</hi> of Reformation, is too large for a ſhort
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40183:5"/> 
               <hi>Preface,</hi> and beyond my <hi>deſigne;</hi> onely this <hi>by</hi> the <hi>by;</hi> I wiſh that Proteſtants (of whatſoever Perſwaſion) would be more ſparing in their <hi>Reflections</hi> upon our firſt <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers;</hi> for beſides the advantage that is hereby given to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Party, we ought to conſider, That abuſes are eaſier complain'd of, then redreſs'd; and poſſibly, had the men of this <hi>Age</hi> been in their ſtead, and under the ſame <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> I do much queſtion (if we may take an eſtimate by their late tranſactions) whether they would have brought the work to ſo good an Iſſue, as through Gods Bleſſing they then did. But no more of this.</p>
            <p>Tis ſufficient for my preſent purpoſe; That ſince the cauſe of their <hi>Separation</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> was to avoid her Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, 'tis evident; That theſe <hi>Ceremonies</hi> which they thought fit to retaine, were (in their Judgment) no part of them, or any other way unlawful; the which, if my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting <hi>Brethren</hi> will but grant, (not to talke now off their <hi>inexpedience,</hi> of which, neither they nor I muſt be Judges) as it is a fair ſtep to end our <hi>Differences,</hi> ſo it hence avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably follows, That if ſome pious men have refus'd the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> others of as great <hi>piety</hi> have <hi>Conform'd</hi> to them; if ſome <hi>Learned</hi> have diſputed, others as <hi>Learned</hi> have defended, which may for ever Silence that Branch of the Objection, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> of their Parties.</p>
            <p>Nor is there much more <hi>weight</hi> in that other part of the Objection, (drawn from their <hi>perſecutions</hi> and <hi>ſufferings</hi>) which comes now to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>A Pretence indeed very <hi>plauſible</hi> and <hi>popular;</hi> for beſides its ſubtle Inſinuations upon a natural ſcore, (we being all obliged by that common bond of Humanity, to compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate thoſe that are in any miſery and trouble, witneſs thoſe uſual reſentments even for a Thief upon the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40183:5"/> it hath this farther advantage; That wherever in Scripture the word <hi>Perſecution</hi> is mentioned, and that either with ſome <hi>Promiſe</hi> annex'd for the ſupport of Gods people (who otherwiſe might deſpond under ſuch gloomy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations) or of ſome Judgment denounced, to reſtrain the fury of their Perſecutors: I ſay, whereſoever ſuch <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages</hi> occur (as they do frequently in holy <hi>Writ</hi>) they have learned the Art (by impoſing upon a credulous <hi>Vulgar</hi>) to make the World believe, that they are thoſe perſecuted <hi>Saints,</hi> for whom thoſe promiſes are recorded, and that all ſuch perſons as are any way employed (though in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Authority) to ſuppreſs them, are Perſecuting wretches, on whom, ſooner or later, all thoſe <hi>Judgments</hi> threatned ſhall certainly be <hi>inflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not in the leaſt offend them with any harſh Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives (ſuch Reflections (though ſome eaſe indeed to a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then'd mind) being very little to the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of a Cauſe) but ſhall only beg their Patience and Charity, whilſt I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to undeceive them, by aſſuring them in plaine <hi>Engliſh</hi> (what, without Repentance, they will one day find true) <hi>That they are not Perſecuted as Saints, but puniſhed as Malefactors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this I ſhall (through Gods aſſiſtance) undenyably <hi>prove</hi> in this Method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By fixing the <hi>Notion,</hi> in laying down a clear and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct <hi>definition</hi> of <hi>Perſecution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By conſidering, how far thoſe preſent <hi>Sufferings</hi> to which our Nonconformiſts are obnoxious, do agree with it, or differ from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perſecution for Religion</hi> (for of ſuch onely I now treat) may not unfitly be thus deſcribed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tis an eager violent inflicting, of outward temporal Evils, for the exerciſe of true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40183:6"/>
            <p>I call it <hi>eager violent inflicting</hi>) ſo the Lat. <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>i. e. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, ſeu con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuato motu ſequor.</hi> inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co affectu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequor. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuò, aſſidue quaero Mart. Lex. Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log.</note> 
               <hi>Perſequor,</hi> and the Gr. <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Heſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> do fully denote; they both ſignifie ſo to <hi>follow,</hi> as a Hunter doth his Prey, who purſues it till he takes it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe theſe terms <hi>eager</hi> and <hi>violent,</hi> do only agree to one ſort of <hi>Perſecution, viz.</hi> That which is <hi>furious</hi> and <hi>rageing,</hi> (it being ſometimes more mild and moderate) and ſince <hi>definitions</hi> do expreſs the <hi>nature,</hi> but not the <hi>degree</hi> of the <hi>thing defined</hi> (as when we define <hi>Calor,</hi> we take no notice of it in <hi>ſummo</hi>) I ſhall therefore omit theſe words <hi>eager</hi> and <hi>violent,</hi> and then the definition (I ſuppoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably) ſtands thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perſecution is an inflicting of outward temporal Evils, for the exerciſe of true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Outward temporal Evils</hi>) either upon the <hi>Body,</hi> as Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, Impriſonment, Tortures, Death; or upon the <hi>Eſtate,</hi> as Pecuniary Mulcts, confiſcation of Goods; or upon <hi>Reputation</hi> and <hi>good Name,</hi> as Slanderings, Revilings, Reproachful Speeches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the exerciſe of true Religion</hi>) which is the <hi>Ratio for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malis,</hi> the Conſtitutive difference, whereby <hi>Perſecution</hi> is diſtinguiſhed from all other violences whatſoever. For let the greateſt <hi>Reproaches</hi> and <hi>Indignities,</hi> uſher in the moſt exquiſite <hi>Tortures,</hi> and thoſe be concluded by a <hi>Death</hi> as cruel, as the utmoſt Malice on Earth, or Fury in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll can contrive; yet unleſs theſe Tortures be <hi>eo nomine</hi> inflicted, for the ſake and cauſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> we may call them mercileſs, inhumane, unnatural Cruelties, (or any ſuch like name as can moſt fitly expreſs them) but not <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Religion,</hi> (that I may yet more fully explaine the <hi>Definition</hi>) I mean the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God; by <hi>true Religion,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40183:6"/> the worſhipping of him according to his Will; the which Will (though heretofore variouſly delivered, and in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Diſpenſations, yet thoſe extraordinary ways of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance being now ceaſed) it hath pleaſed the Goodneſs and Wiſdom of God to deliver in Writing (by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Prophets and Apoſtles) in thoſe <hi>Books</hi> which (by way of eminency) we call the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> So that whatever <hi>Worſhip</hi> is not according to thoſe <hi>holy Oracles,</hi> is not <hi>true</hi> and acceptable, but <hi>falſe</hi> and vain: <hi>In vain do ye Worſhip me,</hi> &amp;c. It being an undoubted Truth; That God hath as much right to appoint the way of his own Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as to be Worſhipp'd.</p>
            <p>There are moreover, we know, <hi>two</hi> parts of Religion; <hi>Credenda, Agenda, Truths</hi> to be believed, and <hi>Duties</hi> to be performed, in order to <hi>Salvation;</hi> and in both theſe, the Scripture is our Rule and Direction.</p>
            <p>He therefore that is <hi>Puniſhed,</hi> either for <hi>believing</hi> thoſe <hi>Truths,</hi> or for <hi>doing</hi> thoſe <hi>Duties,</hi> the belief and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of which <hi>holy Scripture</hi> requireth of him; or he that is <hi>puniſhed,</hi> for <hi>not believing</hi> thoſe things as Truths, which are but falſities and <hi>lies,</hi> or for <hi>not doing</hi> thoſe things as Duties, which are ſinful and <hi>unlawful,</hi> he, I ſay, who is puniſhed upon theſe accounts, is properly <hi>Perſecuted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Caſe</hi> then about <hi>Perſecution,</hi> as it reſpects the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts,</hi> is briefly this:</p>
            <p>If thoſe <hi>Inſtances,</hi> for which they are puniſhed, be no way required of them in <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> either for belief, or practiſe; and if it ſhall appear, upon inquiry, that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> requires nothing of them, that is <hi>in ſide</hi> Erroneous, or <hi>in facto</hi> Impious; if ſhe neither enjoynes them to believe <hi>Lies,</hi> nor to commit any <hi>Sin,</hi> if nor ſo, nor ſo, let the <hi>world</hi> then <hi>judge</hi> where the <hi>fault</hi> lies; and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40183:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> who they are, that (without Repentance) muſt one day <hi>Anſwer</hi> (which I fear is now little thought on) for all thoſe <hi>Separations</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> all thoſe <hi>Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Confuſions, Wars, Murthers, Rapines,</hi> &amp;c. (the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <hi>conſequents</hi> of the former) in the <hi>State,</hi> which theſe poor miſerable divided Kingdomes have ſo ſadly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd.</p>
            <p>'Twill be <hi>replyed,</hi> (and I find it no unuſual Plea) That <hi>Preaching and Praying are neceſſary Duties, But they are puniſhed for Preaching and Praying, Therefore they are puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for performance of religious Duties, and conſequently (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the now mentioned definition) are Perſecuted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They tell us, <note n="e" place="margin">Prop. for Saf. of King and Kingd. p. 10.</note> 
               <hi>There are certain inoffencive perſons, and they</hi> (meaning their Rulers) <hi>have really no more againſt them, only that they meet, and preach, and pray together. Innocent folks, who are dragged to Priſon, for doing nothing in earneſt, but endeavouring to ſave their Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I may, if poſſible, convince <hi>my Brethren,</hi> of the weakneſs and vanity of this plauſible <hi>Argument,</hi> I'le give them my Anſwer (I hope Methodically and clearly) in theſe following Concluſions.</p>
            <p>Concl: 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Preaching and Praying, (as they are the Subject of our preſent Diſquiſition) is meant the performance of them in publick, not in private;</hi> this latter being <hi>liberae obſervation is,</hi> ſince every man (of what perſwaſion ſoever) may not only <hi>Pray</hi> with his own family, <hi>when</hi> and <hi>how</hi> he pleaſeth, but alſo <hi>Preach,</hi> or Inſtruct them (and that without fear of <hi>puniſhment</hi>) in what manner he thinks fit.</p>
            <p>Concl: 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Preaching and Praying there is conſiderable, Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; Circumſtantiae, Res &amp; Modus, the ſubſtance of the</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40183:7"/> 
               <hi>Duty, or the thing to be perform'd, and the circumſtances, or manner of its performance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preaching and Praying, quoad Subſtantiam, are neceſſary, neceſſitate Praecepti &amp; Medii,</hi> i. e. <hi>God hath Commanded,</hi> and the condition of the Church (whilſt Militant <hi>&amp; in viâ</hi>) doth require, that theſe Duties be attended.</p>
            <p>Nor is the <hi>Subſtance</hi> only, but alſo the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of theſe Duties in <hi>Theſi,</hi> and in the general <hi>neceſſary, i. e.</hi> when theſe Duties are conſidered in <hi>actu exercito,</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are put into <hi>practice,</hi> we muſt <hi>neceſſarily</hi> make uſe of Circumſtances, ſome or other.</p>
            <p>Concl: 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Circumſtances (however in Theſi neceſſary) in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſi and in Particular, are not determined in Scripture;</hi> (which, I do not mean as to their Lawfulneſs, but as to their being duties) if they be, there muſt then be produc'd ſome clear and diſtinct <hi>Precept</hi> (perpetually obligatory to the <hi>Church</hi>) requiring our obſervance of ſuch or ſuch Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; for this, and nothing elſe, (though other things are pretended) can conſtitute a Religious Duty. Thus, though <hi>Prayer</hi> be a Duty, yet whether it be a <hi>Set Form,</hi> or <hi>Extemporary?</hi> The <hi>Miniſter,</hi> whether habited in a <hi>Surplice,</hi> or <hi>without?</hi> His <hi>Geſture,</hi> whether kneeling, or ſtanding? The <hi>Place,</hi> whether in a Deske, or at the Communion Table, or at both? So for <hi>Preaching,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Gown, a long Cloak or a ſhort? How many Sermons in one day, whether <hi>three,</hi> or <hi>two,</hi> or but <hi>one;</hi> I ſay, none of theſe, or ſuch like, are determined in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> to be our Duties; thoſe who aſſert they are, muſt produce the <hi>Command</hi> making them to be ſuch; for Duty and Command, have a neceſſary Reſpect and Relation to one another.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40183:8"/>
            <p>Concl: 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Circumſtances (though ſtill free and indifferent</hi> quoad naturam, <hi>being neither commanded nor forbidden yet) muſt not be left undetermined</hi> quoad uſum; <hi>i. e.</hi> Private perſons muſt not be left at liberty, to do what they think fit in <hi>Circumſtantials,</hi> as if an agreement in <hi>Subſtantialls only</hi> were ſufficient; ſo as if there be but <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Praying;</hi> if theſe Duties be but performed, one man may uſe a <hi>Set Form,</hi> another may pray <hi>Extempore;</hi> this <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> may wear the <hi>Surplice,</hi> whilſt his <hi>Neighbour</hi> rejects it as Popiſh and <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi> Does not any man (who hath not enſlaved his <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to ſupport a <hi>Faction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> very eaſily obſerve, that the bare mention of this Fancy (ſuch I am forc'd to call it) is its own Confutation? was it ever ſo much as <hi>thought</hi> on, but in the heat of a Diſpute? Did ever any Conſtituted Church in the world allow ſuch Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty? Are not my <hi>Brethren</hi> themſelves convinc'd of the contrary? If they deny it, I could very eaſily refreſh their Memories in ſo obvious a Theam; I could turn them to their <hi>Directory,</hi> and their <hi>Ordinances</hi> to enforce it, &amp;c. but I ſpare them. In ſhort,</p>
            <p>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Mr. <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes</hi> Serm. at Pauls, Feb. 8. 1646. pag. 18.</note> 
               <hi>There is ſcarce any difference ſo ſmall, and inconſiderable, but the divulging, and propagating of it, may prove dangerous and pernicious, and in the event intollerable:</hi> Therefore to allow <hi>private</hi> perſons the Liberty, to order theſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in the <hi>publick</hi> Worſhip (<hi>pro modulo Conſcientiae</hi>) as their own Conſcience (perhaps humour or intereſt) ſhall <hi>Dictate,</hi> is the ready way to deſtroy all Order and Government in the world. And this I hope is ſufficiently made plain (to any man that will but read and conſider) in the following <hi>Collections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, to riſe yet a little higher.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40183:8"/>
            <p>Since it is neceſſary that there muſt be ſome <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> made uſe of in the exerciſe of theſe Duties, <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Praying,</hi> (it being impoſſible to perform any Action (and therefore Religious Action) without them) and ſince Scripture hath <hi>determined</hi> nothing, either by requiring ſome as <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or forbidding others as <hi>unlawful:</hi> and ſince to leave them undetermin'd (for private Perſons to do what ſeems good in their own eyes) is apparently deſtructive both to <hi>Church</hi> and State; what can more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally follow then this. That they muſt be Determined by the Supream Magiſtrate; who by the Advice of his Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Council, his <hi>Convocation,</hi> (as in Seculars by his <hi>Parliament</hi>) may appoint the performance of theſe, and other Religious Duties in ſuch a <hi>manner,</hi> as is moſt agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that Apoſtolical Canon: <hi>Let all things be done de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and in order.</hi> I proceed therefore to my fifth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, which is this,</p>
            <p>Concl: 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Supream Magiſtrate muſt determine what Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſhall be uſed in the Worſhip and Service of God.</hi> The which Concluſion, I ſhall rather ſuppoſe then prove; not that I think it of leſs truth or certainty then the reſt, but becauſe our Divines, not only <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> but alſo the <hi>diſſenting Parties</hi> (with whom I am now treating) have perform'd it with ſo much plainneſs and ſatisfaction to my hand.</p>
            <p>And though I might collect whole <hi>Volumes</hi> from their Sermons, and other Treatiſes, to confirme this Truth, yet to relieve my ſelf from the drudgery of tranſcribing, (wich is no pleaſing task) and to give eaſe to my <hi>Reader,</hi> I ſhall only refer him to ſome Places in the following <hi>Collections;</hi> which if he pleaſe to turn to, and read (as they are cited
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40183:9"/> in the <note n="h" place="margin">See the Pages fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>viz.</hi> p. 18. 19, 20, 21. 28. 29. 35. 36. 37. 38. 39. 50.</note> Margin) before he goes any farther, he will do me great <hi>right,</hi> and himſelf no diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>From which Places it evidently appears, <hi>That the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is both</hi> Cuſtos <hi>and</hi> Vindex utriuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Tabulae. <hi>That the Examples of the Kings of Iſrael and Judah, may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently warrant and encourage all Religious Magiſtrates, to reform and ſettle Religion in one Vniform way, and take care that all under their Government, ſhould all ſerve the Lord with one ſhoulder, this being not a Tyranny over men, but the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Goſpell. That they muſt take a courſe, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may live a quiet and Peaceable life in Godlineſs and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, not in Strife and Contention;</hi> which how they ſhall be able to perform, if <hi>every man</hi> (concerning theſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances) <hi>may hold what be pleaſe, and Publiſh and Preach what he holds,</hi> I am not able to imagine. Theſe and many the like Paſſages (ſome of which I have now given you in their own words) you will find in the forecited places; from whence I think it is plain, <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>ut ſupra</hi> pag. 20.</note> 
               <hi>That where the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline of the Church doth not, or cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, the Magiſtrate muſt interpoſe his Coercive Power, for Reſtraint or Remedy.</hi> Which leads me to the ſixt Concl.</p>
            <p>Concl. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There muſt be Eccl: Laws, Canons, or Conſtitutions made, for the due ordering of theſe Circumſtances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much I grant hath been objected by my diſſenting B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: againſt theſe <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> both in <hi>Theſi</hi> (againſt all Eccl: Laws in generall) and in <hi>Hypotheſi</hi> (againſt theſe of our own Church in particular.)</p>
            <p>As to the firſt (for the latter is beyond my deſigne) I think it would puzzle the moſt judicious <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> to give a ſolid ſatisfactory Account, why the <hi>Supream Power</hi> may make Laws to determine <hi>Indifferent</hi> Circumſtances in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40183:9"/> 
               <hi>Temporalls,</hi> and not in <hi>Spiritualls;</hi> they being both liable (in my apprehenſion) to the ſame <hi>Difficulties</hi> and <hi>Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences,</hi> and if the latter be <hi>exploded,</hi> the former (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing they are faithfull to their Principles) will very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be <hi>defended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concl: 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Eccl: Laws when rightly made and conſtituted, are obligatory, and muſt be obey'd.</hi> The Reaſon is, Becauſe Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Lawfull Authority <hi>inlicitis &amp; honeſtis,</hi> is a duty, which God in his holy Word requireth of us. Now <hi>that</hi> is lawfull, and conſequently the <hi>debita materia</hi> of any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Conſtitution (Eccleſiaſtical or Civil) which is not contrary to any former obligation. Unleſs therefore the <hi>matter</hi> of theſe Conſtitutions, or the <hi>thing</hi> which they require us to perform, can be evinc'd (by good Logical Deduction) to be contrary to Gods will Revealed in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, there remains nothing but <hi>Obedience,</hi> not onely <hi>Paſſive,</hi> chearfully and quietly (without murmurings and revilings) ſubmitting to the <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> but alſo <hi>Active,</hi> by a ready performance of the thing commanded; though poſſibly it might be thought very inconvenient, as being contrary to <hi>Education, Cuſtome, Intereſt &amp; Advantage in the World,</hi> and the like. And therefore,</p>
            <p>Concl: 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We being not (even the beſt of us all) over-ready in this great Duty of Obedience, There are Penalties annexed to theſe Eccl. Conſt. (as well as to other Laws) to frighten us into our Duty.</hi> Such is the <hi>corruption</hi> and <hi>ſtubborneſs</hi> of our <hi>natures,</hi> and ſo little are we affected with the Obligations of Conſcience, that it is morally impoſſible for the moſt wholeſome Laws to obtain their <hi>End,</hi> without the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Civil <hi>Sanctions</hi> to enforce them. For, if the Laws
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40183:10"/> of <hi>God,</hi> which are holy, juſt and good, and every way perfect, (they being the contrivance of infinite <hi>Wiſdome</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi>) if theſe are contemned and neglected, and (and as ſad experience proves, it) dayly caſt behind our backs, when the obſervance of them is inconſiſtent with ſome Bruitiſh Pleaſure; no wonder if the Laws of <hi>Men,</hi> (who not onely (many times) want <hi>Wiſdome</hi> to contrive, but alſo Goodneſs to deſigne what is moſt profitable for their People) I ſay, no wonder if theſe be rather quarrel'd with and diſputed, then ſubmitted to and obey'd.</p>
            <p>As therefore the infinite <hi>Majeſty</hi> of Heaven, hath enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the obſervance of his Commands, by a ſuitable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of Rewards and Puniſhments; ſo it is the Duty of Inferior <hi>Legiſlators,</hi> to be <hi>a Puniſhment to evil doers, and a Praiſe to them that do well.</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <p>Concl: 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Supream Magiſtrate, in inflicting theſe Penalties,</hi> i. e. <hi>in puniſhing the Offenders againſt his Conſtitutions, doth execute Juſtice, and perform his Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The end and deſign of Government, is <hi>Salus Publica,</hi> it is to take care, <hi>ne quid detrimenti capiat Communitas,</hi> or in the Apoſtles Phraſe, <hi>That we may live a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> This is the End.</p>
            <p>And ſince no <hi>End</hi> can be attain'd, but by a due and effectual Application of proper <hi>Means,</hi> we cannot but in Reaſon grant, that the Magiſtrate may employ ſuch <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium's</hi> as are moſt conducive to his deſired <hi>End.</hi> Amongſt which, <hi>this</hi> certainly is not the leaſt conſiderable, (and without which, all Government is but precarious) viz. <hi>A removal of whatſoever is hurtful and deſtructive to his Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſince the Publick <hi>allowance,</hi> of different Opinions,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40183:10"/> and Practices about Circumſtantials in <hi>Religion</hi> (particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly about Preaching ad Praying) doth naturally improve into contentious <hi>Diſputes,</hi> and thoſe Diſputes (if not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraind) break out into <hi>Civill Wars;</hi> for <note n="k" place="margin">Mr. <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comens Ser. before Parl. Sep.</hi> 12. 1644. pag. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Men will at laſt take up Swords and Spears inſtead of Pens; and defend by Armes what they cannot do by Arguments.</hi> Since things are thus, Tis at leaſt Prudence (if not Duty) in the Supream Power, to remove the Occaſion of this <hi>Ruine,</hi> by enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Publick Practice of theſe Duties in one <hi>Vniforme</hi> way; That all his Subjects <hi>may ſpeake the ſame thing;</hi> and <hi>that there be no Diviſions amongſt them, perfectly joynd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore upon inquiry it do appeare, That the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate</hi> hath Power to make <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> for the better ordering of thoſe <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> about which Scripture hath determind nothing, whether wee muſt uſe or not uſe them; and if <hi>Offenders</hi> againſt theſe Conſtitutions are juſtly puniſhable, it undenyably follows; that in puniſhing ſuch Violaters of his Laws, the Magiſtrate doth not <hi>Perſecute,</hi> but execute Juſtice, and that thoſe Perſons who are thus reflected upon, are not Perſecuted as <hi>Saints,</hi> but Puniſhd as Malefactors. The very Caſe of our Nonconformiſts here in England.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Summary</hi> of theſe <hi>Concluſions</hi> (that my Reader may the better apprehend them to be both <hi>Conſequent</hi> and <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi>) is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preaching and Praying are neceſſary Duties, Which cannot be performd without Circumſtances, Theſe are not determind in Scripture, Nor muſt be left undetermind, Therefore by the Supream Magiſtrate, Who to effect this makes Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, Theſe have Penalties annexd to be inflicted on the Diſobedient, The infliction of theſe Penalties is the execution
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40183:11"/> of Juſtice, and the Magiſtrates Duty, But no Perſecution,</hi> Therefore <hi>thoſe Perſons that ſuffer theſe Penalties are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſely Perſecuted but juſtly Puniſh'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Quod erat Demonſtrandum.</q>
            <p>I cannot at all doubt, but the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of my Brethrens <hi>Argument</hi> (to any unprejudic'd Reader) begins now to appear. However, I will repeat their Syllogiſme once more, and then let the World judge who is in the <hi>Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Preaching and Praying are neceſſary Duties,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But N. C. are puniſh'd for Preaching and Praying,</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> Therefore <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They are Puniſh'd for neceſſary Duties,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>and conſequently are Perſecuted.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> I Anſwer, firſt, by diſtinguiſhing the <hi>Major.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preaching and Praying <hi>quoad Subſtantiam,</hi> are neceſſary Duties, <hi>i. e.</hi> Its neceſſary that theſe Duties be perform'd. <hi>Quoad Circumſtantias,</hi> they are not neceſſary, <hi>i. e.</hi> though theſe Duties be perform'd, yet it is not <hi>neceſſary</hi> to perform them in <hi>ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>manner.</hi> Thus, though <hi>Prayer</hi> be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, yet that it ſhould be <hi>Extemporary,</hi> or without a <hi>Form,</hi> is not neceſſary, or that the Miniſter ſhould be without a <hi>Surplice,</hi> is not neceſſary.</p>
            <p>So for <hi>Preaching,</hi> though it be a Duty, yet to <hi>preach</hi> or <hi>hear</hi> a Sermon in a <hi>Conventicle</hi> of two or three <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,</hi> or to expoſe my ſelf to <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and perhaps, a long Impriſonment, to the neglect of my <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> and thence the ruine of my Family, for which I am bound to provide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſay, to throw my ſelf upon all theſe Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, only to hear a Sermon from <hi>A. B.</hi> or <hi>C. D.</hi> when I may ſafely hear a much better from an Orthodox Miniſter, is ſo far from being neceſſary, that it may juſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Who hath required theſe things at your hands.</hi> That</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40183:11"/>
            <p>Secondly, I Anſwer, by denying the <hi>Minor,</hi> which is utterly falſe and untrue. They are not puniſhed for <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Praying</hi> (they being puniſhable for their neglect) but they are puniſhed for not obſerving thoſe <hi>Circumſtances</hi> about Preaching and Praying, which <hi>Authority</hi> requireth of them; or, they are puniſhed for not performing theſe Duties in ſuch a manner as their <hi>Governours</hi> require; or more plainly yet, they are puniſhed for not obſerving, and ſubmitting to thoſe <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> which their <hi>Governours</hi> have Eſtabliſhed, for the better ordering of theſe Duties. The <hi>Obligation</hi> of which Conſtitutions (becauſe they are much oppos'd) I'le endeavour to <hi>confirm</hi> by this one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. <hi>Bonum non oritur niſi ex integrâ Cauſâ,</hi> There muſt be a concurrence of all requiſite Conditions to make a thing good. Now the Conditions required to the <hi>Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity</hi> of a Law, are not unduely expreſt by the four <hi>Cauſes; Efficient, Material, Formal, Final;</hi> and, <hi>That</hi> Law which is not Defective in any one of theſe, is <hi>Valid</hi> and <hi>Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> But ſuch are the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> Therefore. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Reſpectu Cauſae Efficientis,</hi> there is ſufficient Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Legiſlative Power. 2. <hi>Reſpectu Materiae,</hi> the things enjoyn'd are not unlawful, as being contrary to any Law, any former Obligation. 3. <hi>Reſpectu Formae,</hi> there is ſufficient Promulgation. 4. <hi>Reſpectu Finis,</hi> Publick Peace and Safety, (by reſtraining Diſorders, Tumults, Contentions, which might ariſe from Difformity in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) is the very Reaſon and <hi>End</hi> of their being exacted.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But is not</hi> Conſcience <hi>violated, and</hi> Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberty <hi>infringed by theſe</hi> Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions, <hi>ſince they determine us preciſely</hi> ad unum <hi>in the uſe of Indifferent things, which God and Chriſt have left free</hi> ad utrumlibet?</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40183:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I Anſwer, (referring my Reader for farther Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to Biſhop <hi>Sanderſons</hi> ſeventh Sermon ad Pop. pag. 384.) That there is no <hi>Subject</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (whatever is pretended to the contrary) but hath the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his <hi>Conſcience;</hi> or, (to ſpeak more intelligibly) may worſhip God according to his Conſcience, <hi>i. e.</hi> in ſuch a way and manner as his <hi>Conſcience</hi> (his judging Faculty) judgeth moſt acceptable; provided always, that he keep his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to <hi>himſelf,</hi> or to his <hi>Family,</hi> and make them a Rule only for his own private <hi>Practice:</hi> But if ſuch a man will go <hi>publiſh</hi> his <hi>Opinions,</hi> and entangle the Conſciences of <hi>others,</hi> and ſeek to draw Diſciples after him, and make a Party, and cauſe <hi>Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Diſſentions</hi> amongſt his Majeſties Subjects, and trouble the <hi>Publick,</hi> he is to be reſtrain'd, he is not to be tolerated.</p>
            <p>Object. <note n="l" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Calamys Ser. before the Lords. Dec. 25. 1644. pag. 38.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Will you allow the Magiſtrate to Tyranize over mens Conſciences?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By no means; But I believe it is the Duty of <q>Magiſtrates to keep men from infecting their Subjects with Soul-deſtroying Errours. If thou haſt an Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Opinion, have it to thy ſelf, and the Magiſtrate will not, nay, cannot meddle with thy private Conſcience. But if thou laboureſt to infect others, with thy Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtroying Opinions, I doubt not but the Magiſtrate is bound to keep thee from ſpreading thy Infection to the undoing of the Souls of his Subjects. If he may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhut up a man that hath the Plague upon his body, that he may not Infect others; why not a man that hath the Plague of Hereſie upon his Soul, that ſo he may not deſtroy the Souls of Thouſands? Shall a Maſter in a Family have power to put away a Servant that is tainted with a groſſe Opinion, and yet not be called a Tyrant
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40183:12"/> over that Servants Conſcience? And ſhall not the chief Magiſtrate of a Kingdome have Power to put out of his Kingdome (at leaſt to ſhut up from doing hurt) one that is his Subject, and polluted with Blaſphemous, Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Idololatrical Opinions? Is not the Kingdom the Magiſtrates Houſe and Family?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Theſe are the means that are to be uſed to cure the diſtractions of <hi>England.</hi> The Lord give us grace to put them in practice.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But this and the other <hi>party</hi> will reply, That <hi>they</hi> are neither <hi>Heretical</hi> nor <hi>Turbulent;</hi> and therefore what is all this diſcourſe to <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, No man muſt be Judge in his own Cauſe; every man therefore is to be ſuppoſed ſuch, that (when his Place requires it) refuſeth (by publick <hi>Oaths, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions,</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi>) to give the Magiſtrate aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that he is <hi>Orthodox</hi> and <hi>Peaceable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Mr. <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comen: Serm. at Pauls Feb. 8. 1646. p. 40.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>Poſſibly they will all ſay, They are of the ſame Opinion with the Reformed Churches in Fundamentals, as well as we, and their differences are but in <hi>minutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus.</hi> Now ſuppoſing this to be true (as it may be in ſome of them) why do they then tranſgreſs the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Rule? why do they not if it be in matters of leſſer moment wherein they differ from us, why do not they keep their Opinions private, and have their Faith unto themſelves before God? why do they upon ſo ſmall Differences (if the Differences be ſo ſmall) withdraw from Communion with us, and the reſt of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and gather themſelves into diſtinct and ſeparate Churches?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſupra p. 21.</note> 
               <q>Had all that Profeſs the Goſpel in <hi>England,</hi> made Conſcience to be of the ſame mind, and the ſame Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40183:13"/> with their Brethren, and the reſt of the Churches of Chriſt, as far as poſſibly; and where they cannot, where there is a neceſſity of differing, had they made Conſcience to keep their Differences from appearing in Publick; to have their private Opinions and Faith to themſelves, and not intangle the weak with their doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſputations; forbearing to judge or deſpiſe thoſe that are not of their Opinion, loving them ſtill as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, not cenſuring them as Prophane, Antichriſtian, Fighters againſt God, men that will wilfully ſhut their eyes againſt the Light; had theſe things (I ſay) been attended to on all hands, our Breaches had never been ſo great as now they are, nor ſhould the lovers of Truth and Peace have had ſo much cauſe to lament them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>But, <note n="o" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baxters Cure of Church diviſions,</hi> pag. 254.</note> O the deceitfulneſs of the heart of man! Little do many real Separiſts, who cry out againſt the ſpirit of Perſecution, ſuſpect that the ſame ſpirit is in them! whence is Perſecution, but from thinking ill of others, and abhorring them, or not loving them. And do not you do ſo by thoſe whom you cauſeleſly ſeparate from? <note n="p" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Newco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ut ſupra p. 40.</hi>
                  </note> Who are they that brand their Brethren with the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Proud, Time-ſervers, Prelatical, Tyrannical, Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian?</hi> And what is this leſs then Perſecution?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 2. 1.</note> 
               <q>Therefore thou art inexcuſable, O man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt: for in that thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf, for thou that judgeſt doſt the ſame things. <note n="r" place="margin">Matth. 7. 3. 4. 5.</note> And why beholdeſt thou the More that is in thy Brothers eye, but conſidereſt not the Beam that is in thine own eye? Or how wilt thou ſay to thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let me pull out the Mote out of thine eye; and behold, a Beam is in thine own eye? Thou Hypocrite, firſt caſt out the Beam out of thine own eye, and then
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40183:13"/> ſhalt thou ſee clearly to caſt out the Moat out of thy Brothers eye.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I have a fair occaſion (could I allow my ſelf the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of its improvement) to return my Brethrens Argument upon their own heads, by aſſuring them (and I beſeech God to give them grace to conſider and bewaile it) that the <hi>Perſecution</hi> (ſo much complained of) lyes at their own Doors, they being not innocent <hi>Sufferers,</hi> but injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Aggreſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe I know are very harſh and unpleaſing words; but the Truth of them will appear, when we ſhall have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that there are more <hi>ſorts</hi> of Perſecution then <hi>one,</hi> of which St. <note n="ſ" place="margin">Lib. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. Eccleſ. contr. Peril: Epiſt. cap. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> thus informes. <hi>Gravius per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequitur filius Patrem male vivendo, quam Pater filium caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gando. Et gravius ancilla Saram perſecuta eſt per iniquam Superbiam, quam eam Sara per debitam Diſciplinam. Et gravius Dominum perſequebantur propter quos dictum eſt, ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus domus tuae comedit me, quam eos ipſe cum eorum menſas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertit, &amp; eos flagello de templo expulit.</hi> There is you ſee <hi>Perſecution</hi> of the <hi>Tongue,</hi> and of an <hi>irregular Life,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Hand;</hi> and if my Brethren are not at preſent guilty of this latter (whether through reſtraint, or their own good nature I ſhall not determine) I am ſure the former is their conſtant Practice.</p>
            <p>For, (to inſiſt only upon that) 'tis even amazeing to mention, what bitter <hi>Taunts,</hi> rude <hi>Sarcaſmes,</hi> unmannerly <hi>Jeers,</hi> fabulous <hi>Stories,</hi> ſcandalous <hi>Reproaches,</hi> are their daily exerciſe, whereby they vex the <hi>Righteous Souls,</hi> wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the <hi>Hands,</hi> diſcourage the <hi>Endeavours,</hi> of their honeſt Orthodox Conforming <hi>Brethren,</hi> Are not all <hi>Places,</hi> all <hi>Companies,</hi> all <hi>Occaſions</hi> ſufficient witneſſes of this Truth?</p>
            <p>Really 'tis very ſad, (and to be lamented with <hi>Tear</hi>)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40183:14"/> That the great work of Religion, the Preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and the Salvation of Souls, ſhould be thus obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by theſe unfortunate practiſes.</p>
            <p>But I hope no faithfull Son of the <hi>Church</hi> will be <hi>diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd</hi> at theſe Things, or in the leaſt neglect his Duty, though all the World ſhould be offended at him. The Rule is fixt. <hi>We muſt obey God rather them Man.</hi> 'Tis our Dear Lords caſe, in whom there was no Sin, neither was Guile found in his mouth, and yet he was accus'd for a <hi>Wine bibber,</hi> a <hi>Glutton,</hi> and that he had a <hi>Devill.</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10. 24. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>The Diſciple is not above his Maſter, nor the Servant above his Lord. It is enough for the Diſciple that he be as his Maſter, and the Servant as his Lord: if they have call'd the Maſter of the houſe Beelzebub, how much more ſhall they call them of his Houſhold? Fear them not therefore: Fear not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the Soul; but rather fear him which is able to deſtroy both Soul and Body in Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot now ſtay to expoſtulate with my Brethren, otherwiſe I ſhould tell them, there is ſuch a thing as <hi>Scandal;</hi> and that Chriſt hath <hi>little ones,</hi> the meaneſt of whom, if they offend (hinder from their <hi>Duty,</hi> and ſtop them in their way to Heaven, by ſpeaking Evil of the <hi>Ways</hi> of God) <hi>it were better a Milſtone were hanged about their necks, and they caſt into the midſt of the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall only deſire them to conſider that of Saint James; <hi>If any man among you ſeem to be Religious, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">u <hi>James 1. 26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>bridleth not his Tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this mans Religion is vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baxter ut ſupra p. 245.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>And yet how contrary is the practiſe of no ſmall number of the Religious? In all Companies, how for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward are they to talke of the ſins of Princes and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments? of Courtiers, of Nobility and Gentry, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40183:14"/> of Miniſters? And not onely of the ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that are guilty indeed, but of the Innocent, that are not of their way, whoſe faults they rather <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> make than find.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I have done; and muſt intreat the Readers <hi>Charity,</hi> in pardoning thoſe exceſſes of my <hi>Pen,</hi> which (whilſt I was intent upon the <hi>matter</hi>) may poſſibly have fall'n from mee. God he knows it, (and tis my comfort when the <hi>world</hi> condemnes mee) I have no deſigne to <hi>exaſperate</hi> any man but to <hi>reforme</hi> him. If this do not ſatisfy (for ſome men are very hard to pleaſe) take this farther <hi>Apology</hi> in the words of that Reverend Perſon now mentiond, whoſe <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> I wiſh his Brethren would imitate.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baxter ut ſupra. p.</hi> 251. &amp; 253.</note> 
               <q>Woe to the Land and People that can multiply Sin and cannot Repent; And woe to them that pretend Repentance, and love to be flatter'd in their Sin, and cannot endure to be admoniſh'd, but take all the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verys of their Sin to be injurious reproach. Among the Prophane wee take this to bee a deadly ſign of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency. And is it ſo bad in them, and good in us? It is part of my Office to cry with holy Bradford RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PENT O ENGLAND; and to ſay after Chriſt (Except ye Repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe Periſh,) And can I call men to Repent, when I muſt not dare to tell them of what? nor to mention the Sin which is moſt to be repented of? I uſe all this Preface becauſe I know that Guilt and Impenitency are touchy, and tender, and galled, and querulous, and ſuch will beſtow the time in backbiting their Monitor, which they ſhould beſtow in lamenting their ſin. But ſhall I therefore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, and betray their Souls, and betray the Land
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40183:15"/> through cowardly Silence? Muſt I ſhew that I hate <hi>Profeſſours</hi> by not admoniſhing them, (Lev. 19. 17.) when I muſt ſhew that I love the looſer ſort by my ſharp reproofs? Muſt I not fear them that can kill the Body? and muſt I fear to diſpleaſe a profeſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, calling him to repentance in a time of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Read on now with theſe <hi>Memento's</hi> in your eye: And if after ſo plain a <hi>Premonition,</hi> you will venture to charge mee with that which I diſclaime, do it at your own perill. I ſtand or fall to the Judgement of God, and look for a better reward then the <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> which is, To have the good Opinion of men, be they Profeſſours of Piety, or Profane. And with me by Gods grace, it ſhall hereafter be accounted a ſmall Thing (to the hindering of my Fidelity to Chriſt and mens ſouls) to be judged of men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And if there ſhould be any <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, who inſtead of concurring to heal the Flocks of theſe dividing Principles, ſhall rather joyne with <hi>Backbiters,</hi> and encourage them in their miſreports and ſlanders, becauſe it tendeth to the ſuppoſed intereſt of their <hi>Party</hi> or themſelves, let them prepare to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſuch unfaithfulneſs to their <hi>Conſciences</hi> which will ſhortly be awakned, and to the great Shepherd of the Flock who is at the door, and who told even the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills Agents, that <hi>a Houſe or Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand, but is brought to nought.</hi> Matt. 12. (If alas, alas, experience hath not yet, not yet, not yet, done enough to teach them this.)</q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40183:15"/>
            <head>TOLERATION Diſapprov'd and Condemn'd &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">Humbly preſented to the ſerious Conſideration of all Diſſenting Parties.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Lord Jeſus (who knows all our Hearts, and before whoſe great Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal both you and and I muſt one day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare) is my witneſs; that the cheif deſigne of my preſent undertaking, is the <hi>Peace</hi> and welfare of the <hi>Church;</hi> the continuance of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and the eternal <hi>Salvation</hi> of pretious and immortal <hi>Souls.</hi> I do therefore much hope (though we are all naturally impatient of oppoſition) that you will favourably <hi>receive,</hi> and ſeriouſly <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> theſe <hi>plaine</hi> (yet well meaning) <hi>lines;</hi> which have no other <hi>patronage,</hi> then the <hi>charity</hi> of the <hi>Author,</hi> and the candor and piety of thoſe <hi>perſons</hi> to whom they are <hi>directed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſolemnity</hi> of this <hi>Preface</hi> as it may raiſe your expectations, ſo it may poſſibly invite your
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40183:16"/> rioſity to inquire; <hi>who,</hi> or what manner of perſon I am, that have taken the confidence of ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant an Addreſs.</p>
            <p>And though the knowledge of my name would ſignifie little, (I being not ſo conſiderable as that it ſhould add any weight to my perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance) yet that I may in ſome ſort gratify ſuch obliging <hi>Readers</hi> (as I hope to find you) I ſhall farther acquaint you; that (though I am not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon very ambitious to be known yet) upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, I ſhall either publickly <hi>own,</hi> and <hi>vindicate,</hi> or (if duely convinc'd) as <hi>publickly</hi> recant my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>opinion;</hi> and (in ſhort) to ſecure <hi>you,</hi> and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologize for <hi>my ſelfe,</hi> (ſince concealed names are ever ſuſpitious) I do ſolemnly proteſt: that I am no ſcoffer at <hi>Religion,</hi> nor railer at <hi>true</hi> Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that I <hi>love</hi> an honeſt religious good man (that endeavours to <hi>ſave</hi> his <hi>ſoul,</hi> and come to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) under what profeſſion ſoever I find him: that I will pitty, and (according to my poor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility) rectify, but never make ſport with his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and miſtakes: and herein I doe readily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the learned L <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church of England, in his Refuſe.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 165.</note> 
               <hi>Verulam, That to turne Religion into a Comedy or Satyr, to ſearch, and rip up wounds with a laughing countenance; to intermix
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40183:16"/> Scripture &amp; ſcurrility ſometimes in one ſentence, is a thing very far from the devout reverence of a chriſtian, and ſcant beſeeming the honeſt regard of a ſober man. Two principal cauſes</hi> (ſaith this honourable perſon) <hi>have I ever known of Atheiſme; curious Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and prophane ſcoffing.</hi> And no leſs do I admire (what I hope you will grant I have endeavoured to tranſcribe) that incomparable ſaying of the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious <note n="b" place="margin">The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eccl: Pol Sect. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Hooker. There will come a time when three words uttered with Charity and meekneſs, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a far more bleſſed Reward, then three thouſand volumns written with diſdainful ſharpneſs of Wit.</hi> But, if an irregular <hi>heat</hi> (which I will yet endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſuppreſs) ſhould ſome little diſplay it ſelfe; (it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being very difficult to contend <hi>coldly,</hi> and without Affection, about things which we hold dear and pretious) and certainly the Peace of the Church is eminently ſuch) if <hi>Paſſion,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> ſhould obtrude themſelves under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Zeale (which God knows, is no leſs common then fatal miſtake in the management of our Controverſies) I do then humbly beg of you, that you would ſeriouſly conſider the following Words of the fore-cited <hi>good man;</hi> that, <hi>the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of mens writings muſt not alienate our hearts from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40183:17"/> the Truth, if it appear they have the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now [as far as 'tis judged convenient) given you an account of the Author, t'will in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood be next demanded (ſince this Subject hath been of late ſo fully, and as ſome think unanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably diſcuſt) what convincing Reaſons I have to trouble, either my Brethren to read, or my ſelf to write, ſo common, and (whileſt propoſalls are on foot) ſo unwelcome a diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Really (my Brethren) did I nor fear, that ſuch frequent proteſtations might ſeem too affected; or that <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Reality,</hi> might be miſtaken for <hi>humour</hi> and <hi>deſigne;</hi> I would once more call the ſearcher of all Hearts to witneſs; that I am ſo far from a perſecuting ſpirit (the uſuall <hi>brand</hi> we beſtow upon our Adverſaries) that ſome Months ſince I had ſo favourable an opinion of <hi>Indulgence, Connivence,</hi> or <hi>Toleration,</hi> that I lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thought I ſhould <hi>now</hi> appear an obſtructer of ſo much <hi>deſir'd,</hi> and (as I then apprehended) ſo bleſſed a work.</p>
            <p>I am confident you are very forward to know the Reaſon of ſo ſudden, and unexpected a change; tis therefore (omitting all farther pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing) in ſhort thus.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40183:17"/>
            <p>Being deſirous to informe my ſelfe in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and <hi>extent</hi> of <hi>Toleration,</hi> which I obſerv'd (in ſuch variety of <hi>methods,</hi> by ſuch different <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi>) ſo zealouſly promoted; (and that under no leſs <hi>titles</hi> then <hi>Liberty of conſcience; the great Intereſt of all Kingdomes, and States, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of England</hi>) in order to a more full ſatisfaction (not omitting my hearty <hi>Prayers</hi> to the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Lights,</hi> from whom cometh every <hi>good</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> gift, and who hath promiſed to give <hi>Wiſdome, Counſel,</hi> and <hi>direction</hi> to him that asketh) I procur'd, and peruſ'd, ſome of the moſt conſiderable <hi>Tracts</hi> and Pamphlets (<hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi>) that have handled this Subject: and I muſt <hi>inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly</hi> confeſs (though I was not perfectly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd yet) I did at firſt very much favour (whom I do <hi>yet</hi> no leſs pitty) the diſſenting <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> and really it ſeem'd ſo plauſible (ſince every man muſt anſwer for his <hi>own</hi> works) that every man ſhould have the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his <hi>own</hi> opinion; and the name of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is ſo <hi>ſacred;</hi> that I durſt not but make a <hi>pauſe,</hi> before <hi>I</hi> had paſs'd a <hi>judgement</hi> upon ſuch honeſt pretences. And (to make you my Confeſſors) I was no little affected with ſome <hi>reſentments</hi> of a late ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40183:18"/> Writer; his words are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are a company of People about us in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">c <hi>Propoſ: for the ſafety of King and Kingdome. Pag. 10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Country of different perſwaſions, who meet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times many hundreds together, that our Juſtices have been in perplexity what to do. The moſt of them (for ought I perceive] are certainly inoffenſive perſons, and they have really no more againſt them, then</hi> Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>againſt the Chriſtians of old, when he ſent to</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan <hi>about them, that is, only that they meet, and Preach and Pray together: and if that excellent</hi> Prince <hi>was aſhamed after this report he gave him, of them in his Epiſtle, to have thoſe good men ſought out any more unto puniſhment, I cannot but favour their inclinations, which are a verſe from the like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition. I profeſſe to God it is ſuch an ungentleman like thing (me thinks) to trouble ones Neighbours, that I ſhould be glad to rid modeſt men of that worke. It were better all theſe Acts ſuffered at once a due and Chriſtian regulation, than we ſhould be ſtill put upon, this untoward dragging innocent Folk's thus to Priſon for doing nothing in earneſt, but endeavouring to ſave their ſouls. In the name of God take you your Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let them ſay their Prayers as they will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, together with ſome other reflections drawne from the great Love of Chriſt to <hi>us</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:40183:18"/> (which therefore by way of <hi>gratitude</hi> wee are to <hi>acknowledge</hi> by ſuitable <hi>Acts</hi> of love, pity, and <hi>indulgence</hi> to our poore Brethren) did very much <hi>move</hi> me; The words of my Author are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a perſon I hope you would do a kindneſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 72.</note> 
               <hi>for with all your heart, and you have Reaſon, it is for your dear Lord that bought you, and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world you can do (I am perſwaded) that he will take ſo kindly from you at this time, as to be pitiful to his Servants, who are diſtreſſed about your Acts in point of Conſcience, and who the more deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed they are, and like unto their Lord, the fitter Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects they are for your compaſſion.</hi> And a little after—<hi>If you had no need of mercy from God, it were tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then for you to be extreame towards others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope this candid confeſſion of my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (if yet it be a weakeneſſe to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my errours) ſhall not ſo far prejudice my Reader, as to hinder his acceptance of my fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Reaſons, if it appear that they are really ſuch <hi>(i. e.) rational</hi> and convincing. To giue you therefore my Thoughts in order, my firſt refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was this;</p>
            <p>That though this <hi>Toleration,</hi> whilſt conſidered in the notion, and as it were in the <hi>Idea,</hi> do carry
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40183:19"/> with it a great deal of outward glory and luſtre, filling the hearts of men with expectations of much happineſſe to enſue, (and no wonder if it be <hi>therefore</hi> entertain'd with generall applauſe eſpecially of the Vulgar ſort) yet when we come ad <hi>practicandum;</hi> to conſider how this notion may beſt be made <hi>practicall</hi> and put in <hi>execution,</hi> wee ſhall then meet with ſuch impediments, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, as ſhall render the performance (to ſay no worſe) very far ſhort of promiſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. And for my owne part (ſubmitting ſtill to better judgements) I do find it ſo <hi>unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible</hi> and <hi>unpracticable,</hi> that however it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended (and that very highly) by others, yet in <hi>my</hi> apprehenſion (and indeed the proceſſe of the <hi>World</hi> ſheweth no leſſe) <hi>'tis only a Thing for weaker Parties to talke on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, (to remind you <hi>onely</hi> of what others have more fully diſcuſs'd) if a <hi>Toleration</hi> muſt be admitted, then either <hi>Univerſall</hi> and <hi>unlimited,</hi> (ſuch as may comprehend even the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) or elſe Particular, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) limited to ſome peculiar Perſons or Parties.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, 'tis ſo perfectly wild and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant, that (in the judgement of all ſober
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40183:19"/> Proteſtants) it rather deſerves an exploſive ſcorn then a ſerious confutation.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, <hi>viz:</hi> a <hi>particular</hi> and <hi>limited;</hi> unleſs (which ſeems the likelieſt way to bring the work to ſome <hi>Iſſue</hi>) the diſſenting Parties (who are many and of different perſwaſions) would clearly and diſtinctly acquaint the world, (in ſome publick <hi>Writing</hi> unanimouſly own'd) <hi>who</hi> they are that ſhall be indulged, and upon <hi>what</hi> conditions, we are yet never the nearer.</p>
            <p>They give us indeed (by way of Reſolution) ſome generall expreſſions: but theſe then are of ſo <hi>doubtfull,</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid impoſſible) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation; that I appeal to any rational man (all prejudice and intereſt lay'd aſide) whether ſuch uncertainty's can be laid as a ſufficient <hi>Foundation,</hi> on which to raiſe ſo conſiderable a <hi>ſtructure</hi> as the Peace of the Church, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the Nation.<note place="margin">Diſc. of Relig. Title pag.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For whilſt they tell us of <hi>Reformed Religion to be ſettled in its due Latitude,</hi> and yet never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us what we are to underſtand by this <hi>due Latitude,</hi> what is the full extent, and meaning of the <hi>Word:</hi> whilſt they <hi>propoſe; that the Parties</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſc. of Rel. Par. 1. p. 18.</note> 
               <hi>comprehended in their eſtabliſhment ſhall be of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40183:20"/> in the Publicke Intereſt, and of Principles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous to ſuch ſtated Order in the Church, as the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Commonwealth requires:</hi> and yet never inform us what theſe <hi>important Intereſts,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous Principles</hi> are; what other is it, but to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle us with <hi>Ambiguities</hi> and <hi>Amuſements?</hi> to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble both themſelves and others, in thus fiercely contending for a <hi>Toleration,</hi> in no body know's <hi>What,</hi> and to be granted to no body know's <hi>Whom?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have given you a reflection, which if duely improv'd by ſome happier Pen, might poſſibly appeare of more difficult reſolution, then your preſent <hi>Sentiments</hi> (occaſion'd by the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its delivery) may invite you to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend.</p>
            <p>However, I am ſure (as to mee) it hath been of ſufficient moment to <hi>reviſe</hi> my former Thoughts; and to ſhew leſſe <hi>kindneſſe</hi> to your preſent <hi>Toleration,</hi> towards which I have been (very lately) more warmly affected.</p>
            <p>But (to come yet cloſer to my intendment) that which did more <hi>fully</hi> (and if I miſtake not unanſwerably) convince me, was the peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of ſeverall Sermons preached by ſome of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40183:20"/> our late eminent Divines (before the two Houſes of Parliament) on ſolemn occaſions. For I muſt not omit to tell you, that having heard thoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes much commended (as being delivered by ſuch famous Preachers, before ſuch as were reputed ſo wiſe and judicious Auditors as the <hi>Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> and therefore without doubt did contain ſomewhat extraordinary) I procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a good number of them (about an hundred) and as my other occaſions would permit (not without much expectation) ſet my ſelfe to the reading of them.</p>
            <p>And indeed (that I may be faithfull to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of thoſe Perſons) I muſt acknowledge both to you and the world, I received no bad return of my labours; for I found (which is chiefely to my preſent purpoſe to obſerve) this point of <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> ſo excellently, and fully diſcuſſed (though <hi>obiter</hi> only and as it were <hi>by</hi> the <hi>by</hi>) that no tract <hi>ex inſtituto</hi> (and there are ſome very ingenious) could ever afford me the like ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Now that this may not be <hi>gratis &amp; precario dictum; I</hi> ſhall very <hi>faithfully</hi> lay down their <hi>own</hi> Reaſons in their <hi>own</hi> words; and then leave it to <hi>you</hi> and all men to conſider; whether it be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40183:21"/> not (morally at leaſt) impoſſible; that ſo many <hi>excellently learned,</hi> and eminent Divines, ſhoud ſo frequently, (and that with ſuch vehemency of zeale) oppoſe the very <hi>Name</hi> of Toleration (and which is yet more obſervable, that thoſe very <hi>Sermons</hi> in which theſe invectives are contained, ſhould not only receive the <hi>Thanks</hi> of the two Houſes, but by their eſpeciall order, be likewiſe made <hi>Publick</hi>) were there not ſome ſecret <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> in the <hi>Thing,</hi> which either the <hi>Intereſt,</hi> or <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity</hi> of the preſent <hi>Age,</hi> will not <hi>now</hi> ſuffer us to <hi>apprehend?</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <hi>I ſpeak as unto Wiſe men, Judge ye what I ſay.</hi>
               <signed>
                  <pb facs="tcp:40183:21"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:40183:22"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>Dr. <hi>Cornelius Burgeſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>John Ward.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>William Good.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Thorowgood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Humphrey Hardwick.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Arthur Salwey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>William Reyner.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Caſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>John Lightfoot.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Watſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>George Hughes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Edmund Calamy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Horton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Lazarus Seaman.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Matthew Newcomen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Vines.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Simeon Aſh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>James Cranford.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Edwards.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed> Cujus aures clauſae veritati ſunt, ut ab amico verum audire nequeat, hujus ſalus deſperanda eſt. <hi>Cic. Rhet. l.</hi> 1.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimonies">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40183:22"/>
            <head>The Teſtimonies of the fore-mentioned <hi>Divines againſt Toleration.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <q>GIve me leave, I beſeech you, to ſpeak freely to<note place="margin">Dr. Corn. Burgeſſe Serm. before the houſe of Commons Novemb. 5. 1641. p. 60. Lond. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for C. Meredith at the Crane in St. Pauls Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1641.</note> you; I will do it humbly too.</q>
            </p>
            <p>At your firſt ſitting down, you expreſſed many brave and noble reſolutions, of giving Gods buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the precedency of all other your Affairs: and your beginnings promiſed much. Howbeit, I know not how it comes to paſs, but ſo it is, that Gods work lies yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. Matters of <hi>Religion</hi> lie a bleeding; all <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Church is laid in her Grave, and all putredinous vermine of bold <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and frantick <hi>Sectaries</hi> glory in her aſhes, making her fall, their own riſing to mount our Pulpits, to offer ſtrange fire, to expell the graveſt, ableſt, and moſt eminent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the Kingdome; (if not out of their Pulpits yet) out of the hearts of their People, as a company of weak men, <hi>formaliſts, time-ſervers,</hi> no Miniſters of Chriſt, but <hi>Limbs of Antichriſt;</hi> having no calling ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept from the Devill; and to forſake our Aſſemblies as Babyloniſh and <hi>Antichriſtian;</hi> ſo as in ſhort time they will not leave us the face of a Church. And yet <hi>No Courſe is taken to ſuppreſs their fury &amp; to reduce them to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> which (as things now ſtand) will never be, till you put your hands to the Cure. <note n="b" place="margin">P. 63.</note> I beſeech you therefore, in the Name of that great God, whom you ſerve, and who hath hitherto bleſt you, and for the Peace and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of this Church and Kingdome, to reſume and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40183:23"/> purſue your firſt thoughts of ſetting up God and his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as becomes you in a regular way—<note n="a" place="margin">P. 64.</note> That our Church and the Government thereof may be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger laid waſte, and expoſed to Confuſion, under the plauſible pretence of <hi>Not forceing mens Conſciences.</hi> To put all men into a courſe of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Vniformity</hi> in Gods way, is not to force the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> but to ſet up God in his due place, and to bring all his people into the path of righteouſneſſe and life.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Serm: befor the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons at a publick Faſt March 30 1642 p. 35.</note> 
               <q>Be there none of you that foreſee the fatal miſchiefs of leaving all men to their liberties in the things of God and yet want hearts to uſe your Skill and intereſt to make haſt to ſettle matters of Religion, leaſt you come too late with a Remedy when the diſeaſe is growne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable, and the Kingdome growne to that paſſe (as the grave Hiſtorian noted of old Rome) that it can neither beare the malady, nor endure the Cure. <note n="c" place="margin">P. 46.</note> Do you not ſee or hear dayly of the diſorders, ſects, rents, and Schiſmes that every where bud forth already, and threaten all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Unitie, and Goverment. Give the water but a paſſage without ſpeedy making up the Banks, and you know how ſoon whole Seas will breake in upon us, and render all irrecoverable and incurable. If one difficulty occur to day, it will be doubled, yea multiplied to morrow. There is no <hi>Hydra</hi> ſo fertil of heads, as <hi>Errour and ſchiſme</hi> grown to ſome ſtrength and maturity. It will <hi>aske you but a ſhort time of Connivence, afterwards there well be no curbing nor ſhameing of it.</hi> Nothing is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident as ignorance, impudent as falſhood, and catching as Errour.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Serm: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons at a publick Faſt April. 30. 1645. P. 51. &amp; 52.</note> 
               <q>Take heed of thoſe ſpirits of Errour, who with faire (ſpeciouſe, pargetted, glozeing words) ſeeke to make
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40183:23"/> merchandize of you, beguiling unſtable ſoules. Beware of thoſe compliances with, and indulgences to all ſorts of Sects and Schiſmes now pleaded for, both by word and writing, as it were part of Chriſts Legacy, and his Peoples Liberty to be of what Religion they will; to be tolerated in any opinions never ſo erroneous and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious (untill further light:) that it is the Magiſtrates, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to protect them in that liberty; and that the contrary thereunto is to perſecute Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Hath God inſerted this as one maine branch of his Grand covenant with his People under the Goſpell; <hi>I will give them one heart and one way that they may fear me</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 32. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>for ever,</hi> * that is, <hi>that they may all call upon the name of the Lord to ſerve him with one conſent? Zeph;</hi> 3. 9. Did Chriſt <hi>aſcend up on high and give gifts unto men, and gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, 'till we all come, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. into the unity of the Faith;</hi> and, is it Perſecution, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſme to engage all to <hi>Vnity</hi> and <hi>Vniformity?</hi> Doth Paul bid the Philippians to <hi>beware of the Conciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> Philippians 3. 2. Doth he beſeech the Romans <hi>to marke thoſe which cauſe Diviſions and Offences contrary to the doctrine which they had learned, and to avoid them;</hi> and that upon this ground, that they who are ſuch, <hi>ſerve not the Lord Ieſus but their own bellies, however by good words and fair ſpeeches they deceive the hearts of the ſimple?</hi> Rom: 16. 17. Doth he writing to the Galatians wiſh, <hi>I would they were even cut off that trouble you,</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">And yet the Author of Libert. of Conſc. (p. 32.) tels us that this Text is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the purpoſe.</note> Gal: 5. 12. And is it ſuch an hainous offence now, for the faithfull Servants of Chriſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40183:24"/> to adviſe you to the ſame courſe? O Heavens? be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at this; and bluſh for the ignorance of ſome, and impudence of others, that dare ſo boldly preſſe for ſuch a <hi>Toleration,</hi> which none but vaine deſtructive thoughts of carnall men can look upon, without indignation and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Beware how you hearken to theſe Empiricks and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, who ſeeke to charme the world into a deep ſleepe, by preſenting their confidence of a neceſſity of comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all ſorts of Sectaries, yea of truſting the Sword in their hands, and to defer the ſettling of matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion during the war, for feare of looſing the <hi>Godly</hi> Party (as too many proudly ſtile themſelves, by way of difference from all that are not of their opinions and ways) what is this but to teach God a new forme of Politicks, to proclaime, that it is not alwaies ſafe to hold out the truth of the Goſpel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and to command all men to embrace it, but much ſafer to halt between two opinions? Belike <hi>Joſiah</hi> went beyond his bounds, when after himſelfe had ſworn a ſolemne Covenant to the Lord he made all <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> to ſtand to it, and made all that were preſent in Iſrael to ſerve the Lord their God. 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 34. 32, 33. and <hi>Aſa</hi> much more, when he drew all the people into a Covenant, That whoſoever would not ſeek the Lord God of Iſrael; ſhould be put to death, whether ſmall or great, man or woman 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 13. <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Lib. of Conſ. p. 28. aſſures us the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y when he rells as that</hi> What was done by the Kings of Iſrael &amp; Judah can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably made a rule to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats now under the Goſpell.</note> But the ample and tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcendent Commendations which the Lord gives unto theſe pious Kings, eſpecially in reference to their ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and zeale in reforming and ſettling of Religion in one <hi>Vniforme</hi> way, may ſufficiently warrant and encourage all Religious Magiſtrates, to take care that all under their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40183:24"/> Government, ſhould all ſerve the Lord <hi>with one ſhoulder;</hi> this being not a Tyranny over men, but the Priviledge of the Goſpel, Beware yet at laſt of that thought, that <hi>it is not yet time to build the Lords houſe.</hi> Judah paid dear for this, as I have heretofore ſhewed you at large, on Pſalm: 76. 10. and in my former <hi>Sermon</hi> on this Text, and therefore ſhall ſpare my ſelfe and you, the paines of inlarging at the preſent. Settle this in your hearts; <hi>Gods Truth, the true Worſhip and Diſcipline of Chriſt, ſet up and eſtabliſhed in one Vniforme way, never preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd any Nation or State (where it had free paſſage) in the leaſt degree, but hath ever been their ſafety, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and honour.</hi> It is Errour (how much ſoever cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up) not truth (how much ſoever cryed downe and blaſphemed)</q> that makes and foments rents and factions.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mr. John Ward of Ipſwich in his Serm: before the Commons March 26 1645 p. 49. Lon prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for C. Meredith. 1645.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Honourable and beloved,</hi> yet another word of Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to judge for God, and as God judgeth. 1. for God. There are matters of God, as well as matters of the King or Kingdome; the care whereof muſt be upon you, as well as upon us; his Church, his Kingdome, his City, his houſe, his People, his Spouſe, his Children, his body, ye as nurſing Fathers, muſt tender the good and welfare of them, that they may find harbour and protection, enjoy their juſt priviledges, and Liberties, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with</q> 
               <hi>Chriſt hath made them free: not ſuch licentiouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse as is abus'd for a Cloake of Naughtineſſe.</hi> Ye muſt <q>ſee to order and Unity amongſt them, that there be no rents and ſchiſmes; ſurely our Saviour that aſcended into <hi>heaven and gave gifts to men, ſome Apoſtles,</hi> &amp;c: that <hi>wee might all meet in the Vnitie of faith;</hi> and hath divers times, and after ſundry manners, given that very thing in charge to his miniſters, would not have the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40183:25"/> Magiſtrate left at large from providing, and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that ſpeaking or following the truth in love, we may grow up, making increaſe by edifying our ſelves and one another in Love.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Ye muſt doe that, which we are to pray, that ye doe <hi>viz. Take a Courſe that Chriſtians may live in a Peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quiet life in Godlineſſe and honeſty, not in ſtrife and contention.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>There is—His <hi>Name,</hi> it may not be blaſphemed, diſhonoured. His <hi>Day,</hi> it muſt be ſanctified. His Goſpell. Ye have Authority, and it is your duty to provide that it be duely preached. <note n="a" place="margin">P. 50</note> That it be truly taught:</q> not blended, adulterated, made another Goſpell</p>
            <p>
               <q>His <hi>Worſhip;</hi> it muſt not be corrupted by Idolatry, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious <hi>Innovations,</hi> leſt God be worſhipped in vaine while they teach for Doctrines the Commandments of men. His <hi>Miniſtrie,</hi> it ought to be purged, planted, lights ſet up in every bowle of the Candleſtick, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, maintained, and abetted in the work of the Lord.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>His <hi>Sacraments,</hi> it is your honour as your duty to ſee that they be kept pure in the celebration and miniſtration, of them. There is a book-caſe for it. Num. 9. 7. there were certaine men &amp;c: but if this be not full, the Preſidents. 2 Chron: ch: 15. ch: 30. and ch: 35 will rule the Caſe for the Civill Magiſtrate, and make out this: That where the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church doth not, or cannot prevaile, the Magiſtrate muſt interpoſe his Coercive Power for reſtraint and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy—in a word: God hath many things amongſt us that muſt be protected and maintain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d; and the matters of God have many adverſaries which muſt be watched,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40183:25"/> and <hi>ſuppreſſed;</hi> for ye bear not the ſword in vain, ye are Gods Miniſters <hi>attending continually upon this very thing.</hi> Magiſtrates and Miniſters have (as ye ſee) one common ſtyle of Office; that ye in your place, and we in our Function and Order, ſhould mind and promove the things of God; ye by the <hi>Sword,</hi> and we by the <hi>Word;</hi> you are keepers of both Tables, the firſt and great command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well as the ſecond that is like unto it, both come ſometimes as occaſion is under your cognizance:</q> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">P. 51.</note> 
               <q>And ye know what a brand ſticks to this day upon <hi>Gallio</hi> (though an Heathen Magiſtrate) that he cared not for the matters of the Law and Worſhip according to the Law when queſtion was brought; no, though there were inſurrections and tumults upon that occaſion: and for <hi>Gamaliels</hi> counſell, <hi>Refrain from theſe men and let them alone: for if this counſell or this work, be of men, it will come to naught; but if it be of God, ye cannot over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it, leſt happly ye be found even to fight againſt God</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">If this be true the Auth: of the Prop. for King and Kingdome ſhewed more zeale then knowledge, when ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the Counſell of Gamalielhe thus addes.</note> though it be found within the Bible, yet it is not of like Authority with one of Solomons proverbs or maximes of Policy: it hath no otherwiſe the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God for good, then the deſigne of Pharaoh, or<note place="margin">I wiſh to the Lord, the great Miniſters of our ſtate wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld be content to be no wiſer men then <hi>Gamaliel P. 36.</hi>
                  </note> the crafty counſell of <hi>Achitophel</hi> which are alſo recorded in the ſcripture: it will not conſiſt with other rules of the word, and hath been condemned as unſound, and unſafe by many godly and wiſe men; we have more ſure words of ſcripture out of which we draw the doctrine of the Magiſtrates power and duty in the matters of God and Religion, then the looſe ſpeech of ſuch a Neutraliſt and time ſerving Politician as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> was. Go on there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I beſeech you as you began; take us the little foxes as well as the ravening wolves. <note n="c" place="margin">p. 26.</note> Theſe be they who ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40183:26"/> 
                  <hi>themſelves, ſenſual not having the ſpirit. They</hi> Boaſt indeed (much) of the ſpirit, but they manifeſtly do the works of the fleſh. They plead for <hi>liberty,</hi> but it is <hi>licentiouſneſse. Liberty of Conſcience</hi> they term it, but it is <hi>Liberty of practiſe,</hi> that every man may do what is good and right in his own eyes. They pretend to nothing but <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> and ſeem as if they would be content if they might but have a bare ſubſiſtence in the profeſſion of it. So did the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> to learning, when they firſt appeared upon the Stage, but when they had once inſinuated themſelves into the good Opinion of Princes and States, how well they anſwered the expectations, and required the kindneſſe of thoſe who nurſed them up all the Chriſtian world ſees and fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls to their coſt at this day. They aske But <hi>Connivence</hi> and <hi>Toleration,</hi> but if they once meet in a confluence, and find themſelves ſtrong enough to run in a ſtreame; let but a damme be Pitcht down to reſtraine or oppoſe their madneſſe, or men fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not on, to indulge and grati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y their humour, it would ſoon appeare, whether o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o they would rage &amp; ſwell &amp; get over, or bear down afore them all that ſhould ſtand in their way. They did ſeem a while to cry up the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> and of the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> and have their perſons in admiration, but mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly for advantage, that ſo they may get above all Eccleſiaſticall Authority; &amp; when they are once up to their height, what they will do with the Ladder, they hope to climbe and aſcend by, is not hard to conjecture. They reckon themſelves the <hi>VVheat</hi> in the field, and when once they are ripe, they will eaſily be content to have all that <hi>threſhed</hi> of, by which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their growth. Ye have heard of the fable of the Snake and the Countryman that brought it unto the fire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40183:26"/> I ſhall not need to apply it. Already they begin to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the old land markes and Straiten their bounds they deny their claime up to an high water marke, and make their bankes, and incloſe for themſelves to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry channel ſide. But whether it be holden fit or ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that theſe <hi>Libertines</hi> be decried, for my part, I cannot yet diſcover by any activeneſſe to ſuppreſſe them: onely ſeeing the evil and foreſeeing the miſchiefe, I have given the warning; that at leaſt I may deliver mine own ſoule. <hi>I pray God the remedy be not deferred till it be too late and ye be driven to play an after-game to an extreame hazard and diſadvantage.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Good Serm: before the Comm: March 26. 1645. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for C. Meredith 1645. P. 36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>I doubt not but your Souls abhor that bloody Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net to the ſoules of men, That it is the duty of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to Tolerate all Religions. You have carried out the Duſt behind the door, and this Opinion will bring all the mire in the ſtreets into the houſe of God againe. <hi>Cambyſes</hi> had a luſt to marry his ſiſter, and his Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers told him, there was no law whereby to do it: But with all they told him, there was a law that the Kings of Perſia might do what they liſt, and by this he might marry his Siſter. What is it that ſhall be unlawfull, if this be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for every man to make a Law and Religion for him ſelfe?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Put ſome ſtop by your Authority to the growth of Errours, that are deſtructive, to the power of Godlineſſe, and let not this ſuſpend your ſanction, becauſe ſome that broach them pretend to <hi>Godlineſſe;</hi> an enemy the more like he is to a freind the more dangerous.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>a The third uſe of Confutation; it is of the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40183:27"/>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Sure this Gentleman is miſtaken, I alwaies thought Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrants and Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians had been the ſame.</note> Arminians &amp; Socinians, who endeavour from my<note place="margin">
                     <hi>M. Thomas Thorowgood Serm: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons at a ſolemn faſt Dec. 25. 1644 his Text</hi> Phil. 4. <hi>v. 5. Let your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration be known unto all men Lond prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Chr. Meredith 1645. p. 10</hi>
                  </note> Text to get countenance for that <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Errour, the allowance of all opinions, as if becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith let your moderation be known unto all men, therefore all mens conceits muſt bee born with in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and every one ſuffered in what he ſuppoſeth to be truth. It is a cunning and couſening deviſe, that ſtrikes in with corrupt nature; but becauſe it offers violence to my Text, I cannot be true to it, or you, if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what be not added by way of vindication; and it ſhall be in theſe ſix particulars. Firſt is it probable that our Apoſtle: who elſwhere almoſt every where is ſo zealous for <hi>Vnity</hi> againſt Schiſmes, ſhould in any ſort <hi>Tolerate</hi> them, and ſo voluntarily open a wide doore for <hi>diviſion?</hi> in this very Epiſtle he writes for Peace even paſſionately but with with mighty power <hi>Phil. 2. 1. 2. If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of Love, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any bowells and mercies, fullfill ye my joy, that ye be like-minded, having the ſame Love, being of one accord, and of one mind.</hi> And in the next Chap. 3. 16.—<hi>Let us walk by the ſame Rule, let us mind the ſame thing:</hi> expreſſions different from all licentious Tolerations. The ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle abounds in ſerious Dehortations from Schiſmes and diſſentions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 12. 16. 17. and <hi>as carnall. 1 Cor.</hi> 3. 3. and in other places. And he doth very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten exhort with earneſt words and arguments, not only that we be <hi>like-minded, Rom: 15. 6. Phil.</hi> 2. 2. and of <hi>one mind, 2 Cor. 13. 12. but of the ſame mind. 1 Cor. 10, 10. joyned,</hi> yea joynted <hi>together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgement:</hi> And is here the leaſt approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that multiplying Doctrine? Neither will that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40183:27"/> ſo long as they all breath Chriſt, tend to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Chriſt, it matters not: but let <hi>S. Paul</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer this Objection alſo; is <hi>Chriſt divided? 1 Cor:</hi> 1. 13. Conſider it well, and ſeaſon your Conſideration with that of our Maſter Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Mar. 9. 50. Have ſalt in your ſelves, and have Peace one with another:</hi> If we were preſerved by humility from the corruptions of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opinion, it would be no hard matter to embrace uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Secondly, ſuch allowance would prove deſtructive to holineſs both Perſonall and Domeſticall; <hi>Omnis Religio &amp; nulla Religio,</hi> would ſoon be the ſame: Suppoſe the <hi>Husband</hi> of one Opinion, the <hi>VVife</hi> of another, the <hi>Children,</hi> (it may be) of one or two other, and the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> of as many more; what ſhall the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the houſe do here? how perform the Family duties? diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Opinions, like ſo many hatches interrupting their prayers, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 7. chopping all devotion and piety in pieces: As the Duke of <hi>Wittenberge</hi> was wont to ſay, New Garments introduce new manners, new manners bring in new men, and new men thruſt out the old; ſo new Opinions ſuffered will devour the old; and the <hi>Toleration</hi> of every Religion will deſtroy all Religion, and in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion leave no Religion at all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Thirdly, this Liberty is inconſiſtent with civil tranquility; the bleeding condition of our own nation at preſent is a living, almoſt a dying witneſſe of this; and if that one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of Popery, ſo tolerated as it was, hath brought in upon us ſo many deſtructions; what will that multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do, but haſten deſolation without recovery? for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part would endeavour to ſupport it ſelfe, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the reſt, <hi>et dum de Religione certatum eſt Regio,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40183:28"/> dum de caelo terra amiſſa;</hi> as it was ſaid long ſince.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Fourthly the late <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> may put this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſilence and ſhame; for when not long ſince a <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration</hi> of Popery in that Kingdome was propoſed they ſaid, To give the Papiſts a <hi>Toleration</hi> is a grievous ſin, and will make us acceſſary to all their Abominations and the perdition of all ſeduced ſoules.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Fiftly this may be currant Doctrine amongſt the Turks and <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Defence of Prop. p. 20 highly commends this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the</hi> wiſe <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> Soly. man, <hi>and is ſorry that his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary is of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</hi>
                  </note> the grand Seignior told his Mufti, that is, his chief Prieſt, As a garden is beautified with variety of of flowers ſo his Empire would be adorned with diverſities of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Let ſuch <hi>Toleration</hi> find allowance in the Turk's Paradiſe, it ſhall never, I truſt, be planted in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Sixthly Wee have undertaken all in the National Covenant, the eſtabliſhment of <hi>Uniformity,</hi> and how can that ſtand with <hi>this Omniformity</hi> indeed <hi>Nulliformity,</hi> I underſtand not: it was a prodigiouſe thing in the dayes of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the <hi>Prophet, Jer.</hi> 2. 28. according to the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thy Cities are thy Gods, <hi>O Judah:</hi> here would ſoon appear another kind of multiplying and increaſe; but though this fancy be never ſo plauſible, Divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath ſhut it out of our campe by our Covenant.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">M. Humph. Hardwick Ser. before the Comm: June 26. 1644. Lond print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Chr. Meredith 1645. P. 43.</note> 
               <q>A thing pleaſing to God and profitable to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, by which there is and through Gods bleſſing may be the moſt famous blow given to the whore of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, and her Baſtard Impes that ever yet was: now to have this ſticke among us or laid aſide, whilſt Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Sectaries live in our Boſome, bleſſing, and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret applauding themſelves, that they have neither taken this nor any of your former proteſtations. This is our caſe, and I appeal to wiſer Judgements, whether this may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40183:28"/> not be the way to leſſen the honour and Authority of the high court of Parliament. <note n="a" place="margin">M. <hi>Arth: Salwey be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Com: Octob. 25. 1643 p. 19. Lond. printed for Chr. Mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith. 1644.</hi>
                  </note> Conſider I beſeech you (<hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Chriſtians</hi>) that the vowes of God are upon you, you have abjured <hi>Neutralitie</hi> in your late <hi>Solemne Covenant,</hi> far be it from any of you to glory in luke warm indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency, as if it were a piece of ſingular Policy. You have with your Tongues renounced this Neutrality as deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Follow the Lord in promoting a National Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. You have an admirable Patterne; the zealous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Elijah;</hi> I wiſh from my ſoule that a double portion of his ſpirit may be given unto you, that you may act in his power and ſpirit. <hi>Elijah</hi> oppos'd Idolatry and Oppreſſion; ſo do ye: down with <hi>Baals Altars,</hi> down with <note n="b" place="margin">Arch-Biſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Deans, Chapters. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Baals Prieſts;</hi> do not (I beſeech you) conſent unto a <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration</hi> of <hi>Baals</hi> Worſhip in this Kingdome upon any Politicke conſideration whatſoever—Give me leave to be your humble Remembrancer. The mouths of your Adverſaries are opened againſt you; the hearts of your true freinds are griev'd, that ſo many <note n="c" place="margin">Honeſt Royaliſts.</note> Delinquents are in Priſon, and yet but very few of them brought to their tryal. <note n="d" place="margin">M. <hi>Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reyner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Com. Aug. 28. 1644 Lond. Printed for Sam. En. derby 1644. p. 12.</hi>
                  </note> Ye cannot preach, nor pray <note n="e" place="margin">Errours &amp; Herſy.</note> them down direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and immediately—well, that which the <hi>Word</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do, the <hi>Sword</hi> ſhall; that which the water cannot waſh out the fire will burn out; unto this particular the Apoſtle applies this very <note n="f" place="margin">Haggai 2. 6. 7.</note> Text in part, namely concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſhakeing of the heavens &amp;c: an Earthquake (as we have heard) was appointed to ſhake down the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall ordinances; now if this were neceſſary for the abolition of that divine Worſhip which had ſometimes been by Gods own holy Inſtitution, how much more ſhall that which hath beene of human Invention (yea the very fumes and fogs of the bottomleſſe Pit) to Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40183:29"/> diſpleaſure and diſhonour, be tumbled down with violence, and vengeance to hell, from whence it came.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">M. <hi>Thomas Caſe Serm: before the Comm: May 26. 1647. p. 33. Lond printed for Luke Fawne at the Par. rot in Pauls Church yard. 1647.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>There is a word of Exhortation behind, and I beſeech you ſuffer it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Firſt, to you <hi>Honourable and noble Patriots,</hi> who are called to be Reformers and healers of a poor broken Kingdom. Doth not indeed the <hi>puniſhing</hi> and <hi>ſuppreſſing</hi> of ſpirituall whoredomes againſt God, <hi>Idolatrie, Hereſie, Blaſphemie,</hi> and the reſt: doth it not belong unto you, as well as the puniſhing bodily whoredomes, theft, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp;c:? doth it indeed belong to you only to looke to the civil peace, and to let Religion, and truth, and the worſhip of God ſtand or fall to their own maſter? fight <hi>God,</hi> fight <hi>Divell,</hi> fight <hi>Chriſt,</hi> fight <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> catch that catch can; you have nothing to do but to ſtand by and looke on, ſay ſo then; ſpeake out, publiſh it in your <hi>Declarations</hi> to the world, and let the People of <hi>England</hi> know that it is the right and liberty, to which the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> are borne, that Every man hold what he pleaſe, and publiſh, and preach what he holds; that it is the birth-right (as ſome would have it) of the free born people of England every man to Worſhip God according to his own Conſcience, and to be of what Religion his own Conſcience ſhall dictate. Do ſo and ſee (Fathers and Brethren) how long your Civill peace will ſecure you when Religion is deſtroyed; how long it will be ete your civill peace be turned into civill war, for no doubt if this once be granted them, but they may in good time come to know alſo (there be them, that are inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe principles too) that it is their birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to be freed from the power of Parliaments, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40183:29"/> from the power of <hi>Kings; and to take up armes againſt both when they ſhall not vote and act according to their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</hi> Liberty of <hi>Conſcience</hi> (falſly ſo called) may in good time, improve it ſelfe into liberty of <hi>Eſtates,</hi> and liberty of <hi>Houſes,</hi> and liberty of <hi>wives,</hi> and in a word liberty of <hi>perdition</hi> of <hi>ſouls</hi> and bodies.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Right Honourable and worthy Gentlemen, I cannot ſtand to diſpute, this only would I know of you; are I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, and Hereticks, and Blaſphemers, and Seducers are they evill doers? if ſo, then look to your Charge <hi>Rom. 13, 4. Rulers</hi> muſt be <hi>a Terror to evill Doers</hi> unleſs ye mean <hi>to bear the ſword in vaine.</hi> And if you will God will not; and if God take the Sword into his own hand once, (as he ſeems to be a doing of it) he will ſmite to purpoſe; he will execute vengeance throughly: both upon the evill doers, and upon you that have not been a Terrour to them. Oh therefore up and be doing, that ye may deliver the Kingdome out of the hand of the Lord; for it is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God. O let not your Patience (I hope it is no more all this while) be interpreted a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence, and your Connivence be taken for a Toleration, it may be the Kingdoms ruine,</q> but it will be your ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ser before the Com: Feb. 19. 1645. p. 25.</note> 
               <q>Fathers and brethren how will ye call this keeping of Covenant with God? Had we a Parliament of Apoſtate <hi>Julians,</hi> of whom it is reported, that at what time he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the temples of the Heatheniſh Gods, he ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Chriſtian Churches, call'd home all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians whom he had baniſht, both Orthodox and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and gave them (as we call it) Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but as <hi>Auſtin</hi> more truly phraſeth it, <note n="b" place="margin">Aug. Ep. 166. vid. Ammi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Marcel. lib. 22. p. 208. 209 Edit. Hen: Valeſii. Defence of the Prop. calls this of Julian a brave and Politick thing. p 98.</note> 
                  <hi>Libertatem perditionis,</hi> Liberty to deſtroy themſelves; for that was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40183:30"/> his Policy and end, namely by liberty of all Religions,<note place="margin">Eo modo putans Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men poſſe perire de terris &amp;c.</note> to deſtroy the True, and the Profeſſors thereof too. Or had we a Parliament of careleſs <hi>Gallio's</hi> we ſhould not wonder: but for a Parliament of Chriſtians, Proteſtants, Profeſſors, the Choiſeſt, the moſt active that could be cull'd out of a Chriſtian State, the like not under heaven; that theſe things ſhould be done, and <hi>you hold your Peace,</hi> and be able to keep your places, and <hi>not to put on Righteouſneſs as a Breaſt-plate, and the Garments of Vengeance for your Cloathing,</hi> as it is ſaid of God; this makes the Churches abroad to wonder what Englands Parliament is a doing, and all at home that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt more then their own <hi>Intereſts</hi> and <hi>Notions,</hi> to be filled with unſpeakable trembling and aſtoniſhment, to wit, what God means to do with this poor bleeding Church and State.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ser. before the Comm. Aug. 22. 1645. p. 29.</note> 
               <q>If you mean that England ſhall be turned into a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, and be over-run with <hi>Atheiſme, and Hereſie, and Prophaneneſs, and Blaſphemy,</hi> you may hold your hands, and you need not do it long.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ser. before the Comm: Feb. 19. 1645. p. 25.</note> 
               <q>The Errors and Innovations under which we ſo much groan'd of later years were but <hi>tolerabiles ineptiae,</hi> tolerable trifles, childrens play, compared with theſe damnable doctrines, <hi>Doctrines of Devils,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls them: <hi>Polygamy, Arbitrary Divorce, Mortality of the Soule, No Miniſtery, No Churches, No Ordinances; No Scripture,</hi> yea, the very <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> queſtioned by ſome, denyed by others, And the very foundation of all theſe laid in ſuch a <hi>Schiſme of Boundleſs Liberty of Conſcience, viz: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what you will, and Preach what you Believe,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Lawleſs ſeparation of Churches:</hi> and all theſe not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40183:30"/> only whiſpered in Corners, but Preacht on the houſe top, yea, publiſht in <hi>Print</hi> before your faces with ſo much virulency and impudence, that I verily believe no Age ſince the Apoſtles time could ever parallel.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Sermon before the Commons May 26. 1647. p. 25.</note> 
               <q>There be a Generation of men in the Land that ſtand up for all kind of falſe Worſhip; that every man may <hi>Worſhip God after his own Conſcience,</hi> or if they will not own it in words at length they will have it in figures: And if they may not, are ready, not only to cry, but to act Perſecution, and that to purpoſe: for while they cry <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution gladio oris</hi> they are ready to act perſecution <hi>ore gladii.</hi> I pray God it may never be engliſhed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">M. <hi>John Lightfoot Ser: before the Comm. Aug. 26. 1645. p. 30. Lond-print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for And. Crook at the Green Dragon in Pauls Chur: yard. 1645.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>There is great talk of, and pleading for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> for men to do in matters of Religion, as Iſrael did in the booke of Judges, whatſoever ſeemeth good in their own eyes; and how that proved there, there are ſad ſtories that relate. I ſhall not goe about to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the queſtion, whether the Conſcience may be bound or not, though for mine own ſatisfaction I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved it may, and do hold it a truer point in Divinity that <hi>errans conſcientia liganda,</hi> then <hi>ligat,</hi> but certainly <hi>the Devil</hi> in the <hi>Conſcience</hi> may be, nay he muſt be bound, or elſe you act not according to that vigour that Chriſt hath put into your hands, nor according to that exactneſs that Chriſt requireth at your hands. It is true indeed which is ſo much talked of, that <hi>Chriſt alone muſt reign in the Conſcience,</hi> but it is as true alſo, that <hi>he doth ſo by the Power that he hath put into the hands of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, as well as by his word and ſpirit.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="c" place="margin">M. <hi>Thom: Watſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Com: Decem 27. 1649. p. 17. Lond. Printed for Ra: Smith at the Bible in Cornhil 1649.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>If Conſcience be a ſufficient plea, the Papiſt will come in for a Childs part. Conſcience muſt have a Rule, it binds only <hi>virtute praecepti,</hi> by virtue of a precept. If
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40183:31"/> 
                  <hi>Conſcience</hi> goes againſt the Word, <hi>Deponenda eſt talis Conſcientia.</hi> Get conſcience better informed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">M. <hi>Hughes Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Com: May 26. 1647. p. 34. Lond. Printed for John Roth well at the Sun &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in Pauls Ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>I muſt ſay that the <hi>Toleration of all things muſt be a deſtructive Principle to the State or Church where ever it be allowed.</hi> Experience hath ſhewed us no leſs in Kingdoms and Churches Called by Gods name. Theſe are only ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted which need a larger Treatiſe to ſtate fully. Ye Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt, take heed of yeelding to the pretences of Conſcience, the Devil and not Chriſt hath his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Throne there; And no ſtronger hold for him than Conſcience if he once take it. Chriſt will not ſuffer him to ſhelter there, therefore ye may not, ſo much as in you lieth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Doe not other States, as ſome of the united Provinces<note place="margin">Dub.</note> tolerate all theſe Hereſies, and protect them, and yet they proſper? who more?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I deſire not to deal with other States, unleſs I might do<note place="margin">Sol.</note> them good, I am now only called to our own, yet others being made exemplary, a word in ſoberneſs and truth may not offend. I ſuggeſt only theſe thoughts.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Can any man ſay, that proſperity is a ſign peculiar <q>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Truth? then let Rome come in and ſpeak more than any for outward proſperity.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>Are not ſpirituall wickedneſſes as odious to God as carnall? and are not theſe Hereſies ſuch, which God condemnes as works of the fleſh, inconſiſtent with the Kingdome of Chriſt?</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <q>Hath God made an end yet of viſiting Nations for the ſinnes of them? when God hath done judging were a better time to urge this Example then now. I pray God the evill day may not overtake thoſe States; the good Lord cauſe the Cup of trembling to paſs by them and purge their iniquities peaceably. But I am preſſed in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40183:31"/> Spirit to ſay, God hath not ſpared ſuch State Polities, which have ſought their own riſe by the ruine of God and his Truth. Witneſs <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat,</hi> who made Iſrael to ſin. <hi>And he bids ſin that doth not hinder</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui non ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat peccare cum poteſt jubet.</hi> Sen.</note> 
                  <hi>it when he can</hi>—Gods Truth, my beloved, and not mans example muſt be the Rule—if Hereſies yet muſt be, let us mourn for what we cannot help; it is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable neceſſity when not allowed; <hi>it will be rejoycing in iniquity, either for State or Church willfully to tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">M. <hi>Ed. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamy Ser. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the</hi> Ld <hi>Mayor Jan. 14. 1645. p. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>Though God hath given us glorious victories over our Enemies, yet the Churches of Chriſt ly deſolate, <hi>Church-Reformation</hi> is obſtructed, <hi>Church-Diſcipline</hi> unſetled, <hi>Church-Diviſions</hi> increaſed. The famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London</hi> is become an <hi>Amſterdam, Separation</hi> from our <hi>Churches</hi> is countenanced, <hi>Toleration</hi> is cryed up, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> lyeth aſleep.—<note n="b" place="margin">Ser. before the Lords Dec. 25. 1644. p. 13.</note> It would ſeem a wonder if I ſhould reckon how many ſeperated <hi>Congregations,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Segregations,</hi> there are in the <hi>Citty:</hi> what <hi>Churches</hi> againſt <hi>Churches</hi> &amp;c.—the Lord Knows that I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion theſe things with a ſad heart. <note n="c" place="margin">ut ſupra p. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Diviſions whether they be Eccleſiasticall or Politicall, in Kingdomes, Citties, or Families, are infallible cauſes of Ruine to Kingdoms, Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Families.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="d" place="margin">p. 14.</note> 
               <q>Hereby the hearts of People are mightily diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, many are hindred from <hi>Converſion,</hi> and even the Godly themſelves have loſt much of the power of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> in their lives. I ſay the hearts of People mightily diſturbed, while one <hi>Miniſter</hi> preacheth one thing as a truth of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and another <hi>Miniſter</hi> Preacheth the quite Contrary with as much <hi>Confidence</hi> as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:40183:32"/>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">P. 17.</note> 
               <q>If Diviſions be ſo deſtructive to <hi>Kingdoms, Cities, and Families?</hi> this reproveth thoſe that are the Authors and Fomentors of theſe Diviſions that are now amongſt us. Theſe are the Incendiaries of England. <hi>If he that ſets one houſe on fire deſerveth hanging, much more they that ſet a whole Kingdom on fire.</hi> If he that murders one man muſt be put to death, much more he that Murders three Kingdoms: <hi>Mark them</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Rom. 16. 17.) that cauſe diviſions and Offences contrary to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which ye have Learned and avoid them.</hi> Avoid them as the greateſt enemies of England. Theſe are like the Salamander that cannot live but in the fire of contention. Theſe are of a <hi>Jeſuiticall</hi> ſpirit. And no doubt the heads and hands of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are in all our Diviſions.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">P. 33.</note> 
               <q>Take heed of the Land-deſtroying opinion of thoſe that plead for an illimited toleration of all Religions, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Turkiſme, Judaiſme, &amp;c. The Lord keep us from being poyſoned with ſuch an Error! * This Text<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 25. <hi>Every King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it ſelfe is brought to Deſolation.</hi>
                  </note> riſeth up againſt it, for <hi>it will divide a Kingdome againſt it ſelf.</hi> It will rend it in a thouſand pieces. It is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine directly contrary to your late Oath and Covenant. <hi>A Doctrine that overthroweth all Church Government, bringeth in Confuſion, and openeth a wide door unto all irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Atheiſme:</hi> For at the ſame door that all falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions comes in, the true Religion will quickly get out, and if it be as good for a man to live where nothing is lawfull, as where all things are lawfull; ſurely it is every way as uncomfortable to live where there are all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as where there is no Religion at all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="c" place="margin">P. 37.</note> 
               <q>It is your Duty (Right Honourable) whom God hath betruſted with great Power, to ſuppreſs theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40183:32"/> and Differences in <hi>Religion,</hi> by your <hi>Civil Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> as farr as you are able, leaſt you are acceſſary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. For God hath made you <hi>Cuſtodes utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulae,</hi> Keepers not of the ſecond Table only (as ſome fondly imagine) but of the Firſt Table alſo, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Keepers, but <hi>vindices utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Tabulae,</hi> Puniſhers alſo of thoſe that tranſgreſs againſt either of them. For you are the <hi>Miniſters of God for good, and Revengers, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute wrath upon him that doth evill, Rom.</hi> 13. 4. and God hath deputed you for the <hi>Puniſhment of evill doers, and for the Praiſe of them that do well. 1. Pet.</hi> 2. 19. There be ſome that would blot out halfe your Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and reſtrain this good and evill, to Civil good, and to evils only againſt men. But this is againſt that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Rule, <hi>Non eſt diſtinguendum, ubi Lex non diſtinguit.</hi> Where the Law doth not diſtinguiſh, there muſt not we diſtinguiſh. Tell me I beſeech you, <hi>Shall it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for Magiſtrates to puniſh thoſe that deſtroy mens Bodies, but not thoſe that deſtroy mens Souls?</hi> Shall they be blamed for ſuffering men to draw people away from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Laws of the Land, and to themſelves, and not alſo for ſuffering men to draw away people from the Truth of the Goſpell, and from the ways of God, ſuch as <hi>Hymenaeus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> who <hi>overthrow the Faith of ſome, and their words eat as a Canker?</hi> ſhall Chriſtian Magiſtrates take up the Maxime of <hi>Tiberius, Deorum injurias Diis curae eſſe?</hi> Let God himſelf take care to vindicate himſelf from injuries committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God? as for mee, I will (juſt like <hi>Gallio</hi>) take care of none of theſe things. Can Chriſtian ears endure ſuch Language? Doth not God Propheſy, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 49. 23. That in the New Teſtament <hi>Kings ſhall be our Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40183:33"/> Fathers, and Queens our nurſing Mothers?</hi> And how can a Chriſtian Magiſtrate diſcharge that duty aright if he hath not power from God, to puniſh thoſe that would poyſon the ſouls of his weak Children with Hereſies and ſoul deſtroying opinions?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Will you allow the Magiſtrate to Tyrannize over <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> mens Conſciences?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>By no means. But I believe it is the duty of Magiſtrats <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> to keep men from infecting their Subjects with ſoul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Errors. If thou haſt an Hereticall Opinion, have it to thy ſelf, and the Magiſtrate will not; nay, cannot meddle with thy Private Conſcience. But if thou labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to infect others with thy Grace-deſtroying Opinions, I doubt not but the Magiſtrate is bound to keep thee from ſpreading thy infection to the undoing of the Souls of his Subjects. If he may lawfully ſhut up a man that hath the Plague upon his body, that he may not infect others, why not a man that hath the Plague of Hereſie upon his Soul, that ſo he may not deſtroy the ſouls of Thouſands. Shall a <hi>Maſter</hi> in a Family have power to put away a <hi>Servant</hi> that is tainted with a groſs opinion, and yet not be called a <hi>Tyrant</hi> over that <hi>Servants Conſcience?</hi> and ſhall not the <hi>chief Magiſtrate</hi> of a <hi>Kingdome</hi> have power to put out of his Kingdome (at leaſt to ſhut up from doing hurt) one that is his <hi>Subject</hi> and polluted with blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous, Hereticall, Idolatricall Opinions? <hi>Is not the Kingdom the Magiſtrats houſe and Family?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ser. before the Comm. Octob. 22. 1644. p. 26.</note> 
               <q>This is a certain Rule, <hi>That all the Sins of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which are committed by your connivence or allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, are the Parliament Sins, and they call for a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Repentance.</hi> And therefore I beſeech you ſearch and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40183:33"/> try your hearts, and conſider how far you are acceſſary to the ſins of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> that ſo you may be wrought up not only to a <hi>perſonall</hi> but a <hi>Parliament</hi> humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And if it doth appear, that you have taken more care in ſetling your own <hi>Liberties,</hi> then in ſetling of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> If you have taken more care to build your own houſes then Gods houſe, this is a crying Sin; and this makes you acceſſary to a Thouſand Sins that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Kingdome. Againe, if you do not labour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your duty, and according to your power, to ſuppreſs the <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Hereſies</hi> that are ſpread in the Kingdome; all theſe <hi>Errors</hi> are your <hi>Errors,</hi> and theſe <hi>Hereſies</hi> are your <hi>Hereſies,</hi> and they are your Sins, and God calls for a <hi>Parliamentary Repentance</hi> from you for them this day; You are the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and you are the <hi>Antinominians,</hi> and it is you that hold <hi>That all Religions are to be tolerated</hi> &amp;c. And theſe are your Errors if they ſptead by your <hi>Connivence.</hi> For the Sins of the Sons of old Ely are imputed to old Ely himſelfe. And when the People of Iſrael had prophaned the Sabbath, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with the Nobles of Judah for ſuffering them, and tells them, that it was they that did prophane it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſuffered the People to prophane it, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 17.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>It was none of the Old cauſe that the People ſhould <note n="a" place="margin">M. Ric. Baxter Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Addition to Pref. Prop. 6. Lond printed for Tho: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhil at the Anchor and Bible in Pauls Ch: yard 1659.</note> have <hi>Liberty</hi> and the Magiſtrate ſhould have <hi>no Power in all</hi> matters of Gods Worſhip, faith and Conſcience.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And as it is not the Old Cauſe, ſo it is not a Good Cauſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>For firſt it contradicteth the expreſſe Revelation of the will of God in the holy Scriptures. <hi>Moſes</hi> had to do in matters of Religion as a Magiſtrate; and ſo the ruling
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40183:34"/> Elders of Iſrael that aſſiſted him; And ſo had the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> as is well known, inſomuch that in <hi>Aſa's</hi> days they covenanted to put him to Death that would not ſeek the Lord God of Iſrael. 2. It tendeth to the ruine of the Commonwealth, and therefore it is no good cauſe. How God was provoked <hi>By Aarons Calfe,</hi> and by his Sons, that offered ſtrange fire which the Lord commanded not <hi>Lev.</hi> 10. &amp; what was the effect, &amp; what benefit the Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> brought to Iſrael and Jeroboams houſe, and the high places, and other Errours about worſhip, brought to the Princes and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Judah</hi> we need not particularly recite.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Law and providence are quite changed, if Toleration of falſe Worſhip and other abuſes of Religion, tend not to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the Commonwealth.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>If <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> muſt give Liberty for all to propagate a falſe Religion, then ſo muſt <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Maſters</hi> alſo (for their Coercive power is rather leſſe then the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates then more, and they are no more Lords of faith or Conſcience) But if all Parents and Maſters ſhould give ſuch a Liberty, it would be a crime ſo horrid in the nature and effects, as I am loath to name with its proper Titles.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>A <hi>pari,</hi> it tendeth to the deſtruction of an <hi>Army</hi> to give liberty to all men to do their worſt to draw them to Mutinies and Rebellion. It tends to the ruine of <hi>Families</hi> that all have liberty to do their worſt to tempt the Sons to Theft and drunkenneſſe, and the wife and Daughter to whoredome. It tends to the Deſtruction of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth</hi> if there be liberty for all to perſwade the the People to Sedition and Rebellion: And therefore it muſt tend to the deſtruction of the Church and mens
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40183:34"/> ſouls, and conſequently of the Commonwealth in the cheif reſpects, if all have leave to do their worſt to preach up infidelity, Mahometaniſme, Popery <hi>or any falſe Doctrine or Worſhip,</hi> againſt the great and neceſſary Truths.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I leave it therefore to the judgement of all men that are not faſt a ſleep in their ſecurity, and utterly unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the advantages of the Papiſts, whether this deſigne of engageing the Magiſtrate by a fundamentall conſtitution, not to meddle with matters of faith and Worſhip, but leave them all to Chriſt alone, be not the preſent ſetting up of Popery in England, and the deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the fruit of our labours, Prayers and victories into the Papiſts hands.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But Liberty for <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Prelacy</hi> is ſtil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> by whom?—But if there had been an excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Popery put in, it would have been to little purpoſe, as long as a generall Rule is laid down that condemneth that exception. For if it be the ſtanding Rule, That matters of Religion and faith, and all matters of Worſhip are out of the Magiſtrates power; to ſay then <hi>that Popery ſhall be excepted from Liberty,</hi> is to ſay the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſhall intrude into the proper Office of Chriſt to reſtraine the Papiſts.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Well, ſeeing theſe things are ſo; that ſin will find <note n="a" place="margin">Mr. Tho<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Horton Ser: before the Houſe of Peers. Dec. 30. 1646. Lond prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by F. Neile for Sam: Gelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand at the Brazen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in Pauls Ch: yard. 1646. p. 35.</note> out <hi>us;</hi> let this be the uſe wee make of it, to be carefull to find out <hi>it;</hi> and to begin with that firſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>This is that which lies upon us all: But eſpecially (to ſpeake a word in Seaſon) upon thoſe which have the Government of Kingdomes and Commonwealths com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them. Theſe had need to find out ſin more
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40183:35"/> eſpecially, for the ſafety and welfare of that State, which they have the ordering and managing of.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">P. 36.</note> Firſt their own Perſonall Sins.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">p. 37. &amp; 38.</note> 
               <q>Secondly they are to find out alſo the ſins of the <hi>Kingdome.</hi> I have already Adminiſter'd ſome help in this performance, by the hint of thoſe Sins before mention'd; all which I humbly deſire may be taken into ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and eſpecially (which grows ſo much upon us and which threatens ſo much evil to us) the Sin of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertiniſme</hi> and <hi>Toleration,</hi> which is the ring-leader of all the reſt and involves all others with it. O that this ſhould ever be once mentioned amongſt us here in <hi>England</hi> who have enjoyed ſo much of the Goſpell of Truth as wee have done; derived to us from our Godly fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſealed to us by the blood of the Martyrs, proſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo many Bleſſings, and victories, and Gratious ſucceſſes both of former and latter times, to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration both of Enemies and Friends; is this the fruit and iſſue of all that God hath done for us? and do all over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Reformation come to this? Surely God cannot but take it very ill from us, that we ſhould but incline and leane hereunto; As he ſaid to David of his building of the Temple; Thou didſt well that it was in thine heart and accordingly was well pleaſed with him. So will he ſay to us, of our Contrary carriage; That it is ill that it is in our heart; if ſo be, it be come ſo far, as I hope it is not. What? when we have ſo much appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi> ſhall wee now begin to think of <hi>Indifferency</hi> and <hi>Toleration?</hi> Certainly it's but a ſorry exchange of a Bad Religion for none. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though indeed it will be no exchange, but rather a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confirmation: Toleration of all other Errours doth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40183:35"/> but ſtrengthen Popery amongſt the reſt; <hi>which will at leaſt think ſo well of it ſelf, as to come in for a Childs Part.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">M. <hi>Lazar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Seaman Ser. before the Comm. Sept. 25. 1644. Lond printed by E. G. for J. Rothwell at the Sun in Pauls Ch: yard. 1644<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 41.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>There is a Generation who look for much at your hands, and yet ask nothing, I mean by way of humble Petition. When they find you, or themſelves in ſuch a poſture, as that they cannot be denied, it may be you may hear of them. Beſides the many looſe, prophane, and ſcandalous Miniſters, there are a new ſort riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, who have thruſt themſelves into the Lords Vineyard. It's no leſs then <hi>Perſecution</hi> (ſo they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly give out) to deſire that their ſuſpitious Opinions may be examined according to the word of God, and they commanded to forbear the publiſhing and ſpreading of them for the preſent. There be many dangerous Books abroad, dangerous at leaſt, 'Ile ſay no more.</q>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Liberty of Conſcience.</item>
               <item>The Bloudy Tenent.</item>
               <item>The compaſſionate Samaritan.</item>
               <item>John Baptiſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">p. 44.</note> 
               <q>Conſider alſo, <note n="c" place="margin">Solomons.</note> His failings and beware of them. 1. He had many Wives, <note n="d" place="margin">1 Kings 11. 3.</note> even ſeaven hundred Wives, Princeſſes, and three hundred Concubines. Let not us have as many Religions. There's ſome Analogy between the one and the other. 2. There was in his daies firſt a <hi>Connivance</hi> at Idolatry, then open <hi>Toleration,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> Theſe Wives turned away his heart after other Gods; <hi>v.</hi> 4. He built an high place for <hi>Chemoſh</hi> the Abomination of <hi>Moab,</hi> and for <hi>Molech</hi> the Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40183:36"/> of the Children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> and likewiſe did he for all his ſtrange Wives, <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8. Obſerve the Gradation, firſt <hi>Connivance,</hi> then open <hi>Toleration,</hi> herewithall <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">M. <hi>Matth. New comen Ser: before the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Sept. 12. 1644. Lond. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Ch: Meredith 1644. p. 31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>No Reformation of Religion now: now nothing will ſatisfy ſome, but a <hi>Toleration of all Religions. and all O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions: Church-Government, Diſcipline</hi> is to ſome a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to others <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and <hi>Perſecution,</hi> Ah Brethren, this is a Provocation and will be a Provocation, for this God may turn us into the Wilderneſs again.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">P. 36.</note> 
               <q>We are grown beyond Arminianiſme, Browniſme, Anabaptiſme; we are come (I mean many among us) to down-right Libertiniſme. There are two Opinions, which if encouraged (and they are encouraged if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at) will open a door to Turciſme, Judaiſme A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, Polytheiſme, any monſter of Opinion. The one is. That <hi>every man is to be left to the Liberty of his own Religion,</hi> an Opinion contended for by the <hi>Bloody Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, John Baptiſt, Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and the like Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets. An opinion moſt pernicious and deſtructive, as to the Souls of men, ſo to the Common-weale of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Libertas illa quidlibet credendi</hi> (ſaith Gerard) <hi>nihil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud quam Libertas errandi &amp;c.</hi> That Liberty of believing what men will (or of holding what Faith they pleaſe) is no other then a liberty of erring, and of erring in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that concerns the eternall Salvation of the Soule, wherein to erre cannot but be moſt dangerous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive—Diverſity of Religion diſ-joynts and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts the minds of men, and is the Seminary of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall hatreds, jealouſies, Seditions, Warres, if any thing in the World be; and in a little time, either a Schiſme in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40183:36"/> the State begets a Schiſme in the Church, or a Schiſme in the Church, begets a Schiſme in the State. That is, either Religion and the Church is prejudic'd by Civill Contentions, or Church controverſies and diſputes about Opinions break out into Civill Warrs. <hi>Men will at laſt take up Swords and Spears, inſtead of Pens, and defend by Arms, what they cannot do by arguments.</hi> Once for all, it is the Preſervation and Reformation of Religion which you have Covenanted to endeavour, and not a Liberty of Opinion, that will conſiſt with neither. It is the Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of Hereſy and Schiſme that you have Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which if to be connived at, why doth the Apoſtle reprove the Corinthians for their Schiſme, ſo much? and why doth our Lord Jeſus commend the Angell of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> for trying thoſe which ſaid they were Apoſtles, and were not? And why is the Angell of the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> reproved for ſuffering that woman <hi>Jezabel</hi> who called her ſelf a Propheteſs, to teach and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, <hi>If once we come to this, that any man be ſuffered to teach what he pleaſeth to ſedu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e whom he liſt, to be of what Faith or Religion ſeems good in his own eyes, farewell Covenant, farewell Reformed Religion, farewell the Peace and Glory of England, if that day once come.</hi> But you (Right Honourable) I hope better things of you though I thus ſpeak. I hope while you live and ſit in Parliament, this ſhall never be. It is not uſuall, nay, it is not poſſible that they which love God ſincerely, ſhould deſire to cheriſh differing Religions: for it is moſt certain he that admits contrary Religions, believes neither of them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Serm: at Pauls Feb. 8. 1646. Lond. printed for Ch: Mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith 1646. p. 14.</note> 
               <q>But then the queſtion will be, Seeing there will be difference of judgment and Opinion, while we are upon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40183:37"/> earth, then how, or how far is this difference of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">P. 14.</note> to be permitted? how or wherein may Chriſtians differ from one another in judgement, and yet ought to be Tolerated and born with?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>This is my Brethren a very grave and difficult Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> and to me, conſidering how many places there are wherein the Holy Ghoſt calls upon us to endeavour to be of one mind, of the ſame mind, and of the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is eaſier to tell you, wherein we may not differ in judgement, and wherein differences in judgement may not be <hi>Tolerated,</hi> then to tell you wherein they may.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Firſt therefore, I ſay, that as an abſolute unity in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we ſhould all be of the ſame mind in all things, is ſcarce to be attained in this life, though it be to be endeavoured; ſo an Univerſall and abſolute Liberty of judgement, for every man to differ when he pleaſeth, and in what he pleaſeth, to be of what Opinion and Faith he will, is not to be endeavoured, if it might be attain'd, nor is it to be Tolerated or permitted. I know no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, no pretence of warrant for it, in all the Book of God: Scripture no where ſaith, Let every man be of what Opinion, and of what Faith he pleaſeth, let every man be left to his own judgement.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Particularly, Liberty of Opinion or Judgment is not to be granted, or indulged, in ſuch things as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to God, and Deſtructive to the Souls of men; nor wherein the Difference of judgement and Opinion will neceſſarily and unavoidably, <hi>ex natura rei,</hi> produce a Rent and Schiſme in the Church of Chriſt. 1 <hi>Cor. 1. 10. Now I beſeech you Brethren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40183:37"/> there be no Diviſions among you, but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Rom. 10. 17. I beſeech you Brethren mark them that cauſe Diviſions and Offences among you, contrary to the Doctrine that you have received,</hi> and—what? <hi>Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate them?</hi> no, <hi>avoid them. Gal. 5. 12. I would they were even cut off that trouble you.</hi> Nothing can be clearer then theſe Scriptures are, againſt the <hi>Toleration</hi> of all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and particularly of thoſe that Trouble, Rend, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">P. 18.</note> 
               <q>But (to ſpeak a little to the Poſitive) if there be a Latitude, and a Liberty of judgment left, it is firſt in ſuch things as are not clearly and Poſitively laid down in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and therefore are not of the Fundamentalls, and and eſſentialls of Faith and Worſhip; for there is for theſe, clear and undoubted Light of Scripture.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Secondly, it is in things that are of private and ſingle practice, and not of open converſe, or Church-fellowſhip and Communion. And yet even in theſe things, this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is not to be aſſumed, at leaſt, not to be practiſed without much tenderneſs and circumſpection.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Firſt, care muſt be had of keeping thoſe Opinions wherein we differ from others, private to our ſelves, not troubling or perplexing the Conſciences of others with them. This is the injunction. <hi>Rom. 14. 22. Haſt thou Faith? have it to thy ſelfe before God.</hi> The Faith there ſpoken of, is a particular perſwaſion, touching the free uſe of all Creatures, and the Liberty of all dayes. And this Faith, this Perſwaſion was according to the Truth (as is clear by the Apoſtles Argumentation in that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) yet ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Haſt thou Faith? have it to thy ſelf before God:</hi> do not ſay, I am fully perſwaded of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40183:38"/> my Liberty, and therefore I ought to profeſs it, and hold it out in my practice, whatever become of others; it is the truth of God, and I muſt hold it forth: No ſaith the Apoſtle, have it to thy ſelf. And if a man who hath a private opinion in <hi>re media,</hi> muſt keep it to himſelf, though it be a truth, much more muſt they whoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are falſe and erroneous. <hi>Certainly there is ſcarce any difference of judgement ſo ſmall, and in it ſelf inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, but the divulging and Propagating of it may prove very dangerous and Pernitious, and in the event intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Suppoſe a man ſhould be of this Opinion, that it is unlawfull to eat things ſtrangled, or blood: if ſuch a man keep his opinion to himſelf, and make it a rule only to his own practice: let him enjoy it 'till he can be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe informed, and perſwaded in his Conſcience. But if he will now go publiſh this Opinion, and intangle the Conſciences of others, and ſeek to draw diſciples after him, and make a party, and cauſe Diviſion and Diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt the People of God, this is not to be tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Private Perſons of a differing judgement, if they live quietly, frequent the publick Aſſemblies of Worſhip, and are not diſcerned to diſturb the Peace either of State or Church, by any ſecret underminings, are to be tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, in hope of their Converſion, and for publick Peace ſake. But if theſe men ſhall begin to ſpread their Errors in publick, to inveagle and draw others to them, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile the ſimple, and ſo to trouble the publick Peace, they are to be reſtrained.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">P. 21.</note> Had all that profeſs the Goſpel in England, made Conſcience to be of the ſame mind, and the ſame judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40183:38"/> with their Brethren and the reſt of the Churches of Chriſt, as far as poſſibly; and where they cannot, where there is a neceſſity of differing, had they made <hi>Conſcience</hi> to keepe their diffences from appearing in <hi>Publick,</hi> to have their private opinions and faith to themſelves and not intangle the weake with their doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Diſputations; forbeareing to judge or deſpiſe thoſe that are not of their opinion, loving them ſtill as <hi>Brethren,</hi> not cenſuring them as Profane, Antichriſtian, fighters againſt God, men that will willfully ſhut their eyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Light; had theſe things (I ſay) beene attended to on all hands, our breaches had never beene ſo great as now they are, nor ſhould the lovers of truth and Peace have had ſo much cauſe to lament them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">P. 40</note> 
               <q>But where is the fault you will ſay? True it is there are diviſions, ſad diviſions, danger threatening diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, but where is the fault? I know there are many that lay all the fault upon thoſe whom they call Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, and ſay it is their rigour, and their pride and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, their Spirit of Domination that is the cauſe of all theſe diviſions; Thus ſay the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> and thus the <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> and thus the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and thus the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay. Now the Lord judge between us and them, and let his people that hear judge this day.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Who are they that divide in judgement from all the Reformed Churches of Chriſt in the world, that have Opinions and judgements differing from the Opinions &amp; judgements of all the Reformed Churches? we or the <hi>Anabaptiſts?</hi> we or the <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> we or the—? Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly they will all ſay, they are of the ſame Opinion with the Reformed Churches in fundamentalls, as well as we, and their differences, are but <hi>in minutioribus.</hi> Now ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40183:39"/> this to be true (as it may be in ſome of them) why then do they tranſgreſſe the Apoſtles rule? why do they not if that it be in matters of leſſer moment wherein they differ from us, why do not they keep their opinions private, and have their ſaith unto themſelves before God? why do they upon ſo ſmall differences (if the differences be ſo ſmall) withdraw from Communion with us and the reſt of the Churches, and gather themſelves into diſtinct and ſeparate Churches?—their holding one head &amp; one faith, doth not excuſe them from being guilty of breach of Unity and downright Schiſme, ſo long as they hold not one body, one baptiſme. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſive</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Beza annot. in 1 Cor. 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>eſt cum alii aliis &amp;c.</hi> Schiſme or diviſion (ſaith he) is this; When men are ſo addicted to ſome men, or to ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward rites, that though they do agree in the cheif points of Religion, yet they are eſtranged in their minds, and engage themſelves into parties and factions. Now who are they that though they profeſſe to agree with us in Doctrine have yet made a ſeceſſion, withdrawne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves gathered Churches, engaged Parties? Conſider and give ſentence.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Who are they that have moſt broken the band of Love? There is great fear what the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> will do if once they get power into their hands; but in the meane time what do others? who are they that brand their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with the Title, <hi>Proud, Time-ſervers, Prelatical, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical, Antichriſtian?</hi> And what is this leſſe then <hi>Perſecution.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Who are they that haue been fartheſt from conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to their Brethren for peace and union ſake? were it fit, I could ſay ſomething of this, yea much: I could tell you much hath beene yeelded and much more
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40183:39"/> would be yeelded, yea almoſt any thing, but that one thing that would lay a foundation of perpetuall <hi>Diviſion</hi> and diſ-union in <hi>Families, Church, Kingdome?</hi> Who are they that profeſs an utter impoſſibility of reconciliation or union, and plead for nothing but <hi>Toleration, Toleration,</hi> and ſome for <hi>Toleration</hi> in the utmoſt Latitude, to <hi>Papiſts, Jews, Turks,</hi> the very artifice whereby the <hi>Arminians</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> ſought to gain a party, and ſtrength unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? Reſolve theſe Queſtions, and they will reſolve you who are moſt guilty of theſe Diviſions.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">M. <hi>Rich: Vines Ser. before the Com: Mar: 10. 1646. Lond. print. for Abel Roper. 1647 p. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>By a Declaration ſet forth above Thirty years agoe, King <hi>James</hi> (of Famous memory) was pleaſed to let the World know, not only how ill he reſented, and how much he deteſted the <hi>Vorſtian,</hi> and <hi>Arminian</hi> Doctrines, then newly born and in their ſwadling-cloaths; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo how ſollicitouſly he interpoſed with the States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the United Provinces, againſt their admittance of <hi>Vorſtius</hi> into the place of <hi>Divinity</hi> Profeſſor of <hi>Leiden,</hi> or into their Country. And that he might decline the envy of being in <hi>alienâ Republicâ curioſus,</hi> he bears him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon that common rule, <hi>Paries cum Proximus ardet,</hi> when a Neighbours houſe is on fire, it concerns all in the Neighbour-hood to look about them. This Vigilancy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes our (I know not what to call it, I wiſh no worſe might be ſaid then) inſenſibleneſs and ſecurity. For what were thoſe ſparkes at that time ſmoaking in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote corner, in compariſon of that fire which now flames forth at every corner of our houſe, blown up by that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or liberty of all <hi>Religions,</hi> which may be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, the Golden Calfe of theſe times, whereunto many are not unwilling to contribute their ſtrength &amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, and whoſe Birth-day, they would not fear to call <hi>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40183:40"/> Jehovae,</hi> an acceptable day unto the Lord. Are not the errors which are rife amongſt us, either by infecting Perſons of Place and Quality, grown into that boldnes? or by carrying away <hi>Barnabas</hi> alſo, crept into that cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit? or by ſpreading far and wide, riſen to that ſtrength? that they do face, if not ſeem able to put into danger of rowting, our common Faith, Publick Worſhip, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Miniſtry, long and much expected, and promiſed Reformation. This to the common Enemy, is the <hi>Cape of good hope;</hi> the ſound part are afraid, leaſt the Truth ſhould come to beg for poor quarter, and be led Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, following the Chariot of triumphant Liberty. Some think that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in his <hi>Pontificalibus,</hi> may by this means be retrived, and recalled from exile, to which it was ſentenced by the <hi>Covenant.</hi> Many that are as diſtant in their Opinions as the two Poles, yet moving upon one axeltree, or tyed together by the tayles of common Intereſt, doubt not but by laying their ſtocks together they ſhall be able to bid fair for a <hi>Toleration.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And that we might not be left alone to wonder at our ſelves, our ſympathizing Brethren abroad do wonder alſo, That we ſhould be made the common Sewre to receive the Garbage of other Churches, and that their ſtinking ſnuffes ſhould be allowed Candleſticks here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>In this ſad Poſture of things, all mens eyes have been upon the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and every one ſaith, <hi>Is there no Balme in Gilead? Is there no Phyſitian there? Why then is not the health of the Daughter of my People recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">M. <hi>Simeon Aſh Serm. before the Lords Feb. 26. 1644. Lond. print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Edw. Brewſter 1645. p. 32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>Endeavour vigorouſly to compound our Differences in Eccleſiaſticall concernments. Alas, alas, my heart
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40183:40"/> akes, becauſe of our breaches. Let mine eyes run down with tears night and day, and let them not ceaſe, for the Virgin Daughter of my People is broken with a great breach, with a very grievous blow, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. 17. What Factions and Fractions, what <hi>Schiſmes</hi> and Sepatations, what Rents and Diviſions are in this poor, diſtracted, Diſtreſſed Church of <hi>England?</hi> how ſhould either King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or Church divided ſtand? <hi>God forbid, but tender reſpect ſhould be had to tender Conſciences. But</hi> (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable) <hi>I beſeech you take heed, leaſt under that pretext, you think of Tolerating all Religions amongſt us.</hi> Such Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (I am afraid) would uſher in Libertiniſme, and haſten our deſolation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mr. <hi>James Cranford Serm. before the L. Mayor Feb. 1. 1645 Lond. print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Char: Greene 1646. p. 11. &amp; 12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>It is commonly replied in Pulpits, in Preſſes, That a <hi>Toleration</hi> of all conſciences, even Antichriſtian, would be a Soveraign remedy to cure all diſſentions, and an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall means to compoſe the Wars of Chriſtendome: all the blood that hath for ſo many years been ſhed, is charged upon the reſtraint of this licentiouſneſs, <hi>ignorantly or malitiouſly termed Perſecution.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I anſwer, it is beſides my purpoſe to diſcuſs this queſtion of Toleration, only for the preſent I enquire, Firſt; Would theſe men that ſo hotly defend it, grant that <hi>Toleration</hi> (if they had power in their hands) to others which they deſire for themſelves? I doubt it. The <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> did ſometimes ſeem as earneſt enemies to <hi>Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> as theſe men; yet when they had <hi>Authority</hi> on their ſide, they raiſed <hi>Perſecution</hi> againſt the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> more terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then the heathen Emperours againſt the Chriſtians, which the Churches of the Eaſt moſt grievouſly <note n="b" place="margin">Binii Tom. 1 conc. p. 686.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Athanaſius</hi> at large deſcribeth, and having ſpoken
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40183:41"/> much of their inhumane, and more then belluine cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty againſt all Sexes, all Ages, both living and dead, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Solitar.</note> that he had ſaid leſs then their inhumanity was, becauſe it exceeded all expreſſion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did ordinarily plead for <hi>Toleration,</hi> and ſeemed the moſt inveterate enemies to all diſturbance for <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſake; yet when under the Apoſtate <hi>Julian</hi> they had gotten power, who can declare (ſaith <note n="a" place="margin">Con. lit. Petil: l. 2. c. 82.</note> 
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi>) what havock they made of the Orthodox? <note n="b" place="margin">Opt. cont. Parm. l. 2. 3.</note> All <hi>Africa</hi> was filled with blood and deſolation; Men were rent, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons dragged, Infants ſlaughtred, Women with child miſcarried, none were ſecure in their houſes, the wayes were not ſafe for Travelers; the Letters of them that boaſted to be the <hi>Captains</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> were ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to all. Are our men led by another Spirit? Sure I am, that one of them, that with moſt earneſtneſs, or impudence pleads for <hi>Toleration,</hi> was lately of another mind in the caſe of <hi>Familiſts</hi> and <hi>Antinomians</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="c" place="margin">P. 13.</note> 
               <q>Secondly would ſuch <hi>Toleration,</hi> conduce to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of Peace in the Common-wealth? hath it ever done it? Poſſible it is, that the equality of Powers may perſwade each Party for a Seaſon to ſuppreſs their inward rancour; can <hi>Toleration</hi> take it away, ſo that it ſhall not break out upon ſenſible advantages by the increaſe of ſtrength? let the experience of former Ages, and preſent times</q> teach this.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Errour may Tolerate errour, <hi>ſaevis inter ſe convenit urfis,</hi> but can darkneſs agree with light? or <hi>Wolves</hi> with <hi>Sheep?</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. cont. Haeret. c. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> obſerves concerning <hi>Hereticks</hi> of old, they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed well enough one with another; for though they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in private opinions, yet they joyned in one, in the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40183:41"/> oppoſing of Truth. You <hi>Perſecute</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi> of the<note place="margin">P. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Donatiſts</hi>) where you are able; where you <hi>Perſecute</hi> not, you are not able to doe it, reſtrained by the fear of Laws, or envie, or the multitude making reſiſtance.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I have been long upon this poynt; but I will conclude it, with that ſolemn Embaſſie, which the Orthodox Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Aſſembled in Councell at <hi>Sirmium,</hi> ſent to the Emperour <hi>Conſtantius.</hi> I have inſiſted the longer, <note n="a" place="margin">Athan. de Syn. Arim. &amp; Sele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that it might appear to all, that the Toleration of Errour, is not a way to Peace, as ſome men pretend, but to diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and confuſion: And yet I am not an enemy to Peace, but a friend to Truth, and Holineſs, without which no Man ſhall ſee God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>A ſeriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; paſſionate Admonition to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; in the words of</hi> M. <hi>Tho. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in his</hi> Gangra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>part. 1. p. 84 Lond. print. for Ralph Smith at the bible in Cornh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll 1646.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>Miniſters ought now to be intent to the errours of the times, both in Doctrine and Practiſe, and obſerve what is the proper work of the day, and Preach accordingly, taking heed of being guilty of ſinfull ſilence, whileſt Chriſt and his truth ſuffers. We have too many wounds with which we have been wounded, in the houſe of our friends: many Miniſters have and doe undoe us; ſome by their totall ſilence; others by ſpeaking too favourably of the Sects, and too much daubing; 'tis high time now to ſpeak out, when the truth of God, the Faith once delivered to the Saints, more pretious then our lives, is almoſt loſt, three Kingdomes almoſt ruin'd, and all the reformed Churches in their Truth and Peace hazarded. They that can now be ſilent, well contented, and let the Wolves come freely and not barke, they deſerve to be accounted dumb dogs. Let therefore, all Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Miniſters, who would not have all run to ruine, ſtir up themſelves, and lift up their voices like Trumpets, ſtand no longer looking on, as idle ſpectators, or halting
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40183:42"/> between two; for he that is not now with God in his cauſe is againſt him, and he that gathereth not ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth—And that Miniſters in our times may be a means to prevent and ſuppreſſe the Errours, <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> they muſt not onely often preach againſt them, but they ſhould ſet themſelves againſt all the ways by which Errours are come in, and are farther comeing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and oppoſe them by Preaching &amp; writing; as Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Preaching, the Gathering of <hi>Churches,</hi> and above all a <hi>Toleration,</hi> for that would be an open doore, at which all kind of <hi>Hereſies</hi> would come in, and no man could keep them out: and therefore if Miniſters will witneſſe for Truth and againſt Errors, they muſt ſet themſelves in a ſpeciall manner againſt a <hi>Toleration,</hi> as the principall inlet to all <hi>Hereſie</hi> and Error; And if a <hi>Toleration</hi> be granted all preaching will not keep them out: For as it hath been anſwered the Patrons of Images, (who plead let them ſtand, but Preach againſt the VVorſhipping of them) that if they ſtand, preaching will not take away all the danger; tis not ſufficient to keep the People from all Idolatry; ſo ſay I in this caſe. If a <hi>Toleration</hi> be granted, the Devill will be too hard for us, though we preach never ſo much againſt them. <hi>A</hi> Toleration will undoe all. Firſt bring in Sceptiſme in Doctrine, and looſenes of Life, and afterwards all Atheiſme.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The Patrons of Error, becauſe they cannot at firſt plead for ſuch and ſuch Doctrines <hi>in terminis,</hi> and yet hold them, and would have them propagated, therefore they plead for a Toleration, which once being granted they will come in then of courſe. O let the Miniſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore oppoſe Toleration, (as being that by which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel would at once lay a foundation for his Kingdom to all
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40183:42"/> Generations) witneſſe againſt it in all places, poſſeſſe the Magiſtrate of the Evill of it, yea, and the People too, ſhewing them how if a Toleration were granted, they ſhould never have peace in their Familes more, or ever after have command of VVives, Children, Servants, but they and their Poſterities after them are like to live in diſcontent, and unquietneſſe of mind all their dayes.—<note n="a" place="margin">p. 87.</note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> might ſhew how the Paſtors of the Reformed Churches (namely thoſe who were ſtars of the Firſt Magnitude) were againſt the Toleration of Anabaptiſts, Libertines, and other Sectaries in their time, and what they did and writ againſt it; as <hi>Calvin, Zuinglius, Peter Martyr, Philip Melancthon, Zanchius, Beza, Knox, Bullinger, Muſculus,</hi>—<note n="b" place="margin">p. 88.</note> As alſo how in <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Queen Elizabeths dayes,</hi> learned Biſhops and Godly Miniſters were againſt the ſuffering of many Religions in this Kingdome: as Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Babington,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> who in his learned workes on <hi>Revel:</hi> 2. 20. ſpeakes thus; <hi>Every man is not to be left to his own Conſcience; to teach and hold what Doctrine he will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But all ſuch men or women as teach erroneous Doctrine, by the Government of the Church are to be reſtrained.</hi>—<note n="c" place="margin">p. 91.</note> Did I ſay <hi>the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Doctors, Court-Chaplains,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops-Chaplains,</hi> (for there were ſome of all theſe ſorts oppos'd) hazard the favour of King, Nobles, great Courtiers, the loſſe of all their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, <hi>Arch-Biſhopricks, Biſhopricks, Deaneries,</hi> great liveings to withſtand a <hi>Toleration;</hi> And ſhall the Miniſters of our times ſuffer a <hi>Toleration</hi> of all Sects to come in upon us, in a time when the greateſt Reformation is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that ever was in this Kingdome, and a Parliament fitting, and be either wholly ſilent or oppoſe ſaintly; be
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40183:43"/> afraid of diſpleaſing ſome great man, or hazarding a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle eſtate and liberty? was the Lukewarme Angel whom God hath caſt out of his Church, for not being zealous enough, yet ſo zealous as to hazard all againſt a <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Popery?</hi> And ſhall the <hi>Presbyterians Orthodox</hi> Godly Miniſters be ſo cold as to let <hi>Anabaptiſm, Browniſme, Antinomianiſme, Libertiniſme, Independency,</hi> come in upon us, and keep in a whole Skin? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Biſhops and their Chaplains ſhall riſe up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Miniſtry of this Generation, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared againſt the mind of the King, Council, and ſo powerfull a faction as was for Popery, and the <hi>Toleration</hi> of it in thoſe dayes, if they be ſilent or meally mouthed, beſides the ſhame and diſhonour of it here, before the Churches abroad, and good men at home, who will lay all the blame upon the Miniſters, and ſay, Wee may thanke them for this, for dealing no more freely, nor faithfully with the Kingdom, crying out, an unworthy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſembly, an unworthy Miniſtry in City and Country, to ſit ſtill and ſuffer all theſe Errors and poyſonous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, in Books, Sermons to come in upon us, and to paſſe unqueſtioned.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>O for ſome <hi>Gabriel Powells, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wnams, Abbots</hi> &amp;c:<note place="margin">O for a <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> a <hi>Calamy,</hi> a <hi>Caſe,</hi> a <hi>Baxter,</hi> an <hi>Edwards &amp;c. to write Preach, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> to write, preach, remonſtrate, proteſt againſt the Errors and wayes of theſe times. Tis want of courage and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out hath undone us; and 'tis onely boldneſſe and freedome in ſpeakeing, to declare particularly ſuch books come forth, ſuch Sermons preached, ſuch practices plaid, ſuch perſons preferred and ſuffered, ſuch partiality uſed &amp;c: in reference to the Sectaries, that muſt reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us; theres no way to put a ſtop to things, and ſave all from ruine, but preſent courage and Heroick reſolution,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40183:43"/> 
                  <hi>and lets ſpeak out, and ſuffer no longer a company of giddy cunning ſelf-ſeeking Sectaries, to betray the Truth of God, and to abuſe and undoe two Kingdoms</hi>—Lets therefore fill all <hi>Preſſes,</hi> cauſe all <hi>Pulpits</hi> to ring, and ſo poſſeſs Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, City, and whole Kingdom againſt the Sects, and of the evill of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> and a <hi>Toleration,</hi> that we may no more hear of a <hi>Toleration,</hi> nor of Seperated Churches, being hatefull names in the Church of God. <hi>AMEN AMEN.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">An Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of M. Nath: Newcomen Serm. at Pauls Feb. 8. 1645. p. 12.</note> 
               <q>For if it be lawfull for every man to entertain and hold what opinion he pleaſeth, how differing ſoever from the opinion and judgment of the reſt of the Church and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, yet this is his opinion, and his judgement is perſwaded of it, and he muſt follow his own judgement, and this liberty of judgement be (as ſome ſay) <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> part of the Liberty purchaſed by Jeſus, and to reſtrain it, or ſet bounds to it, is in their language <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, Tyranny, &amp;c.</hi> If this were true, ſure <hi>Paul</hi> did ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill, to charge the <hi>Corinthians</hi> with ſo much authority, <hi>to be of the ſame mind, and of the ſame judgment.</hi> Might not ſome among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> have ſaid to <hi>Paul,</hi> This is hard uſage, this is to <hi>rack a low man to the ſame length with a taller, and to cut a tall man to the ſtature of one that is low?</hi> What, the <hi>ſame judgement?</hi> and the <hi>ſame minde?</hi> will not <hi>Paul</hi> allow <hi>difference of lights and ſights?</hi> Might not ſome <hi>one</hi> among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> have ſaid, What if I am of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that there is no reſurrection, what hath <hi>Paul</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man to do with that? it is my conſcience, and it is my liberty, and what hath any man to do with my conſcience more then I with his? might nor <hi>Hymaeneus</hi> have ſaid; What if it be my Opinion, <hi>that the Reſurrection is paſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready,</hi> what hath <hi>Paul</hi> to do with that? Yes, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40183:44"/> if ye perſiſt obſtinate I will Excommunicate you, <hi>I will deliver you up to Satan, that you may learn not to Blaſpheme:</hi> Certainly this ſhelter, this Aſylum of errour, falſely called <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> was not thought of in former times.</q>
            </p>
            <p>THus far theſe Famous Divines, whoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words I have tranſcribed, and that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, never adding ſo much as one ſyllable of my own, unleſs in the Margin, where I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken a little Liberty.</p>
            <p>I do much hope (upon a ſerious peruſall) you will confeſs theſe <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> both pertinent and convincing, and therefore I might here take occaſion to conſult my own eaſe, and your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. But becauſe (as I have found by ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience) <hi>Prejudices</hi> are ſtrong, and evil <hi>Habits</hi> (which have been long in contracting) are not ſuddainly removed, (as an effectual <hi>meanes</hi> (through Gods bleſſing) of your farther <hi>Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) I</hi> ſhall intreat your peruſall of theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Authorities.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:40183:44"/>
            <head>A LETTER <hi>OF THE</hi> Presbyterian Miniſters in the City OF LONDON, <hi>Preſented the Firſt of</hi> Jan. 1645. <hi>to the Reverend Aſſembly of</hi> DIVINES, Sitting at Weſtminſter by Authority <hi>of Parliament AGAINST</hi> Toleration.</head>
            <head>
               <pb facs="tcp:40183:45"/>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:40183:45"/> To Our Reverend, Learned, and Religious Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the Prolocutor, and the reſt of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines Aſſembled, and now ſitting at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, by Authority of Parliament: Theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and beloved Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE are exceedingly apprehenſive of the <q>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirableneſs of our Churches Peace, and of the pleaſantneſs of Brethrens Unity, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that when Peace is ſet upon its proper Baſis, <hi>viz:</hi> Righteousneſſe and truth, it is one of the beſt Poſſeſſions, both delectable and profitable: like <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> ointment, and the dew of <hi>Hermon.</hi> It is true, by reaſon of different lights, and different ſights among Brethren there may be diſſenting in Opinion; yet, <note n="a" place="margin">What is the keeping conventicles or private meetings but ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from our Church communion.</note> 
                  <hi>why ſhould there be any ſeparating from Church-Communion?</hi> The Churches Coat may be of diverſe colours, yet, why ſhould there be any rent in it? Have we not a Touch-ſtone of Truth, the good word of God; and when all things are examined by that word, then that which is beſt may be held faſt; but firſt they muſt be known, and then examined afterward. If our diſſenting Brethren after ſo many importunate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties would have been perſwaded (either in zeale to the truth, or in ſincere love to the Churches peace, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40183:46"/> among Brethren, or in reſpect to their own reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by faire and ingenious dealing, or <note n="b" place="margin">Yet the Miniſters of this perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made as little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, Promiſes, yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oaths of Canonicall Obedience to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oceſans.</note> 
                  <hi>in Conſcience to their promiſe made with the Miniſters of London now five years ſince,</hi> or any ſuch like reaſonable conſideration) at laſt to have given us a full narrative of their Opinions, and Grounds of their Separation, we are perſwaded they would not have ſtood at ſuch a diſtance from us as now they do: But they choſe rather to walk by their own private lights than to unboſome themſelves to us their moſt affectionate Brethren; and to ſet themſelves in an untroden way of their own, rather then to wait what our Covenanted Reformation, according to the word of God, and <note n="c" place="margin">Shew us the example of one refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth her Miniſters liberty not to uſe her eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhd Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> 
                  <hi>examples of the beſt reformed Churches</hi> would bring forth. But the offence doth not end here, it is much that our Brethren ſhould ſeparate from the Church, but that they ſhould endeavour <note n="d" place="margin">This is plainly our Brethrens deſigne and endeavour at this time.</note> 
                  <hi>to get a warrant to Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize their Separation from it, and to have Liberty (by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing members out of it) to weaken and diminiſh it, till (ſo far as lies in them) they have brought it to nothing; this we think to be plainly unlawfull, yet this we underſtand is their preſent deſigne and endeavour.</hi> Wherefore (Reverend Brethren) having had ſuch large experience of your zeale of Gods glory, your care of his afflicted Church, your earneſt endeavours to promote the compleat Reformation of it, and of your ready concurrence with us in the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any means that might be found conducible to this end; we are bold to hint unto you theſe our enſuing Reaſons againſt the Toleration of Independency in this Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>The deſires and endeavours of Independents for a Toleration, are at this time extreamly unſeaſonable and preproperous: for,</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:40183:46"/>1. <q>The Reformation of Religion is not yet perfected and ſetled amongſt us, according to our Covenant. And why may not the Reformation be raiſed up at laſt, to ſuch purity, and perfection, that truly tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may receive abundant ſatisfaction, for ought that yet appears?</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>It is not yet known, what the Government of the Independents is, neither would they ever yet vouchſafe to let the World know, what they hold in that point, though ſome of their Party have been too forward to challenge the <hi>London Petitioners, as led with blind Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and pinning their ſoules upon the Prieſts ſleeve,</hi> for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring an eſtabliſhment of the Government of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there was any Modell of it extant.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <q>We can hardly be perſwaded, that the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents themſelves (after all the ſtirs they have made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us) <note n="e" place="margin">The Pres<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byterians (although often preſſed thereunto) will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they would be all concluded, how far they mean to goe, and where to ſtay in their deſires of Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention.</note> 
                  <hi>are as yet fully reſolved about their own way, wherewith they would be concluded,</hi> ſeeing they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh not their modell (though they are nimble enough in publiſhing other things) and they profeſs Reſerves, and new Lights, for which they will (no doubt) expect the like Toleration, and ſo <hi>in infinitum.</hi> It were more ſeaſonable to move for Toleration, when once <hi>they are poſitively determined how far they mean to goe, and where they mean to ſtay.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <q>Their deſires and endeavours, are unreaſonable, and unequall in divers regards.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>
                  <hi>Partly becauſe no ſuch Toleration, hath hitherto been eſtabliſhed (ſo far as we know) in any Chriſtian State by the Civil Magiſtrate.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>It's noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery <hi>would not in the late times tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Partly, becauſe ſome of them have ſolemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that they cannot ſuffer Presbytery; and anſwerable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40183:47"/> is their practiſe in thoſe places where Independency pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <q>And partly becauſe <note n="g" place="margin">To grant indulgence unto a few, would offend many more of all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Why may not Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and all other Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the ſame favour, in caſe they provide Readers or Churches.</note> 
                  <hi>to grant to them, and not to other Sectaries, who are free borne as well as they, and have done as good ſervice as they to the Publick (as they uſe to plead) will be counted injuſtice and great Partiality;</hi> but to grant it unto all, will ſcarce be clear'd from great impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. <q>Independency is a Schiſme</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <note n="h" place="margin">Ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready do, &amp; (in caſe your Tolera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion be granted) will draw our members from our Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which ye acknowledge true Churches.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Independents do depart from our Churches and ſo acknowledg'd by themſelves.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>
                  <hi>They draw and ſeduce our members from our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <note n="i" place="margin">Ye do in effect ſet up Separate Churches.<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>They erect ſeparate Congregations, under a ſeparate</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>and undiſcovered Government.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ye receive not the Sacraments (except ſome few) in our Churches but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> private meetings,</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>They refuſe Communion with our Churches in the Sacraments.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <q>
                  <hi>Their Miniſters refuſe to preach among us as Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <q>
                  <hi>Their members, if at any time they joyne with us in hearing the Word and Prayer, yet they do it not as with the Miniſteriall Word and Prayer, nor as the Acts of Church Communion</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>No Schiſme is to be Tolera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as ye grant. But Presbytery is a Schiſme</hi> Now, <hi>as much as Independency w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> by you declared to be</hi> Then. <hi>Therefore, (according to your own grounds) it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not to be Tolerated.</hi>
               </note> Now we judge that no Schiſme is to be <q>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Church <note n="*" place="margin">Schiſmes.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1. 10. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12. 25. <note n="*" place="margin">Diviſions.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom:</hi> 6. 17. with 1 <hi>Cor. 3 3. Gal:</hi> 5 20.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. <note n="m" place="margin">The ſame would follow if Presbytery were Tolerated.</note> 
               <q>Many miſchiefes will inevitably follow upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:40183:47"/> this Toleration, and that both to Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt to the Church, as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>
                  <hi>Cauſeleſs and unjuſt revolts from our Miniſtry, and Congregations.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>
                  <hi>Our Peoples minds will be troubled, and in danger to be ſubverted, as Acts</hi> 15. 24.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <q>
                  <hi>Bitter heart-burnings among Brethren, will be fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and perpetuated to Poſterity.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <q>
                  <hi>The Godly, painfull, Orthodox Miniſtry, will be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and deſpiſed.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5, <q>
                  <hi>The life and power of Godlineſſe will be eaten out by fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous diſputes, and vaine janglings.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <q>
                  <hi>The whole courſe of Religion in private Families, will be interrupted and undermined.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <q>
                  <hi>Reciprocall Duties between perſons of neareſt and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Relations will be extreamly violated.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <q>
                  <hi>The whole work of Reformation, eſpecially in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Government will be retarded, diſturbed, and in danger of being utterly fruſtrate and void, whileſt every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall have liberty, upon every triviall diſcontent at Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall Goverment and Churches, to revolt from us, and liſt themſelves in ſeparated Congregations.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <q>
                  <hi>All other Sects and Hereſies in the Kingdome will be encouraged to endeavour the like Toleration.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>All other Sects and Hereſies in the Kingdome will</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>ſafeguard and ſhelter themſelves under the wings of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, and ſome of the Independents in their Books, have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly avowed, that they plead for Liberty of Conſcience as well for others as for themſelves.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. <q>
                  <hi>And the whole Church of England, in ſhort time will be ſwallowed up with deſtruction and confuſion. And God is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40183:48"/> not the Author of confuſion but of peace. 1. Cor:</hi> 14. 33.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Secondly to the Commonwealth. for,</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>
                  <hi>All theſe miſchiefs in the Church will have their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable influence upon the Commonwealth.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>
                  <hi>The Kingdome will be wofully weakned by ſcandalls and Diviſions; ſo that the enemies of it, both domeſticall and forreign,</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>will be encouraged to plot and practice againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>It is much to be doubted, leſt the power of the Magiſtrate,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>ſhould not onely be weakened, but even utterly overthrowne, conſidering the Principles and practices of Independents, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their compliance with other Sectaries, ſufficiently</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">And are not Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples known to be ſo too.</note> 
                  <hi>knowne to be Anti-Magiſtraticall.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">And as inconſiſtent with other Oaths im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Lawfull Authority, which that was not.</note> V. <q>Such a Toleration is utterly repugnant and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with that ſolemn League and Covenant, for Reformation and defence of Religion, which not only both houſes of Parliament, but alſo perſons of all ſorts in both Kingdoms of England and Scotland, have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and with hands lifted up to the moſt high God have ſworn: <note n="a" place="margin">Which Oaths have been taken by moſt of the chief ſticklers for Toleration, and with a True intention (it was hoped) to performe the ſame.</note> which Covenant likewiſe, both you, and we, and thoſe that moſt earneſtly purſue the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of Toleration, have made (or ſhould have made) <hi>in the preſence of Almighty God, the ſearcher of all hearts, with a true intention to perform the ſame, as we ſhall anſwer at the Great day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed. For,</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>
                  <hi>This is oppoſite to the Reformation of Religion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40183:48"/> to the word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches, Article</hi> 1.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <note n="n" place="margin">The To<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leration of Presbytery is no leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and uniformity of all the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes then Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>It is deſtructive to the three Kingdomes neareſt conjunction and uniformity in Religion and Government, which might lead us and our poſterity after us as Brethren to live in faith and Love Art.</hi> 1.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <note n="o" place="margin">Seeing Presbytery is as much a Schiſme from Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, as Epiſcopacy or indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency was from Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, why do they now, in stead of extirpation, deſire the Toleration of it, contrary to your Covenant.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>It is plainly contrary to that extirpation of Schiſme and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the Power of Godlineſſe, which we have ſworne ſincerely, really, and conſtantly to endeavour without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <note n="p" place="margin">Toleration of Schiſme rendreth Magiſtrates and Miniſters acceſſary to the Errours, Sins, and Deſtruction of ſeduced and deluded People.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Hereby we ſhall be involved in the guilt of other mens ſins, and thereby be endangered to receive of their Plagues Art.</hi> 2.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>It ſeems utterly impoſſible (if ſuch Toleration ſhould be</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>granted) that the Lord ſhould be one, and his name one in the three Kingdomes. Art,</hi> 2.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <q>
                  <hi>This will palpably hinder the Reformation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, inevitably divide one Kingdome from another, and unhappily make factions and parties among the People con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this League and Covenant; of which evil offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whoſoever ſhall be found guilty, are reputed in the Words of the Covenant</hi> 
                  <note n="q" place="margin">The Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of deformity, even in little Matters, ſometimes cauſeth factions and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties amongſt the People. Let <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s have a care we be not Incendiaries, or evill Inſtruments for Sacrilegious ſpirits to work by ill affected as well to Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as Epiſcopacy</note> 
                  <hi>Incendiaries, Malignants
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40183:49"/> Malignants and evill Inſtruments, to be diſcovered, that they may be brought to publick triall, and receive condigne puniſhment. Art. 4. &amp;</hi> 5.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Theſe are ſome of the many Conſiderations, which make deep impreſſions upon our ſpirits, againſt that great <hi>Diana</hi> of Independents, and all the Sectaries ſo much cryed up by them in theſe diſtracted times, <hi>viz.</hi> A Toleration, a Toleration. And however, none ſhould have more rejoyced then our ſelves in the eſtabliſhment of a Brotherly, Peaceable, and Chriſtian accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet this being utterly rejected by them, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſſemble how upon the fore-mentioned grounds, we deteſt and abhor the much endeavoured Toleration. Our Bowels, our Bowels are ſtirred within us, and we could even Drowne our ſelves in Tears, when we call to mind, how long, and ſharp a travell this Kingdom hath been in for many years together, to bring forth that bleſſed fruit of a pure and perfect Reformation; and now at laſt after all our pangs, and dolours, and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, this Reall and through Reformation, is in danger of being ſtrangled in the Birth, by a lawleſs Toleration, that ſtrives to be brought forth before it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Wherefore (Reverend and Beloved Brethren) we could not ſatisfy our ſelves, till we had made ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of our Thoughts unto you about this matter; not that we can harbour the leaſt jealouſy of your zeale, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, or induſtry in the oppoſing, and extirpating of ſuch a root of gall and bitterneſs, as Toleration is and will be, both in preſent and future Ages; but that we may what lies in us, endeavour mutually to ſtrengthen one anothers reſolutions, againſt the preſent growing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40183:49"/> and that our Conſciences, may not ſmite us ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day for ſinfull ſilence, or ſluggiſh deficiency in any point of Duty, tending to the glory of Chriſt, Honour of the Truth, Peace of the Church, Perfection of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Performance of our Covenant, and Benefit of preſent and ſucceeding Generations.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Sion-Colledge</hi> Lond. <date>Decemb. 18. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Subſcribed by <hi>Us</hi> your Affectionate Brethren, and Fellow-labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, to whom Truth and Peace is very pretious.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="judgment">
            <pb facs="tcp:40183:50"/>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:40183:50"/>
            <head>The Judgement of King <hi>JAMES</hi> and His Privy-Council againſt Toleration.</head>
            <head type="sub">Tranſcribed verbatim out of Judge <hi>Crooks</hi> Reports. Term. Mich: Anno 2. <hi>Jacobi</hi> Parag. 13. Part. 2. p. 37.</head>
            <p>MEmorandum, that by command from the King, <q>all the Juſtices of England, with diverſe of the Nobility <hi>viz.</hi> The Lord <hi>Elleſmere</hi> Lord Chancelor, the Earle of <hi>Dorſet</hi> Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, Vicount <hi>Cranbourne</hi> Principall Secretary, the Earle of <hi>Nottingham</hi> Lord Admirall, the Earles of <hi>Northumberland, Worceſter, Devon,</hi> and <hi>Northampton,</hi> the Lords <hi>Zouch, Burghley,</hi> and <hi>Knowles,</hi> the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of the <hi>Dutchy,</hi> the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>London, Popham</hi> chief Juſtice, <hi>Bruce</hi> Maſter of the <hi>Rolls, Anderſon, Gawdy, Walmeſly, Fenner, Kings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mill, Warberton, Savill, Daniell, Yelverton,</hi> and <hi>Snigg,</hi> were aſſembled in the Star Chamber; where the Lord Chancellor, after a long Speech made by him, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Juſtices of Peace, and his Exhortation to the Juſtices of Aſſize; and in diſcourſe concerning Papiſts and Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40183:51"/> Declaring how they both were diſturbers of the State, and that the King intended to ſuppreſs them, and to have the Laws put in execution againſt them, Deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Juſtices their Reſolution in three things.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Firſt, Whether the Deprivation of Puritan Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters by the High Commiſſioners, for refuſing to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelves to the Ceremonies appointed by the laſt Canons, was Lawfull? Whereto all the Juſtices anſwered.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That they had conferred thereof before, and held it to be lawfull, Becauſe the King hath the Supream Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Power, which he hath Delegated to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, whereby they had the Power of Deprivation, by the Canon Law of the Realm, and the Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> which appoints Commiſſioners to be made by the Queen, doth not confer any new Power, but explain and declare the ancient Power. And therefore they held it clear, That the King without Parliament might make Orders and Conſtitutions for the Government of the Clergy, and might deprive them, if they obeyed not; And ſo the Commiſſioners might deprive them. But they could not make any Conſtitutions without the King, and the divulging of ſuch Ordinances by Proclamation is a moſt gratious Admonition; And for as much as they have refuſed to obey, they are lawfully deprived by the Commiſſioners <hi>ex Officio</hi> without Libell <hi>Et ore tenus convocati.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Secondly, Whether a Prohibition be grantable againſt the Commiſſioners upon the Statute of 2. <hi>H.</hi> 5. if they do not deliver the Copy of the Libell to the Party; whereto they all Anſwered, That that Statute is intended where the Eccleſiaſticall Judge proceeds, <hi>Ex officio &amp; ore tenus.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:40183:51"/>
            <p>
               <q>Thirdly, Whether it were an offence puniſhable, and what puniſhment they deſerved, who framed Petitions, and collected a multitude of hands thereto, to prefer the King in a publick cauſe as the <hi>Puritans</hi> had done, with an Intimation to the King, That if he denyed their Suite, many Thouſands of the Subjects would be diſcontented? Whereto all the Juſtices anſwered, that it was an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence finable at diſcretion, and very neer to Treaſon and Felony in the puniſhment, for they tended to the raiſing of Sedition, Rebellion and diſcontent among the People: To which Reſolution all the Lords agreed and then many of the Lords declared.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That ſome of the <hi>Puritans</hi> had raiſed a falſe Rumour of the King, how he intended to grant a <hi>Toleration</hi> to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: which offence the Juſtices conceived to be heinous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finable by the Rules of the Common Law, either in the Kings Bench, or by the King and his Councill: or now ſince the Statute of 3. H. 7. in the Star-Chamber. And the Lords ſeverally declared how the King was diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, with the ſaid falſe Rumour, and had made but the day before a Proteſtation unto them, That he never intended it, and that he would ſpend the laſt drop of blood in his body before he would do it; and prayed that before any of his Iſſue ſhould maintain any other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then what he truly profeſſed and maintained, that God would take them out of the World.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="votes">
            <pb facs="tcp:40183:52"/>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:40183:52"/>
            <head>VOTES &amp;c. <hi>OF THE</hi> Honourable Houſe of COMMONS <hi>Feb. 5. &amp;c.</hi> 1662. Upon Reading His Majeſties Gratious <hi>Declaration and Speech &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <date>Die Mercurii 25. Feb. 15. Car. R.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>Reſolved &amp;c. <hi>Nemine contradicente, That the humble Thanks of this Houſe, be returned to His Majeſty, for his Reſolution to Maintain the Act of Vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reſolved &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it be preſented to the Kings Majeſty, as the Humble Advice of the Houſe, That no Indulgence be granted to the diſſenters from the Act of Vniformity.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Gratious Soveraigne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, of the Commons houſe of Parliament, did with great joy receive your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40183:53"/>
               <q>moſt Gratious Speech, at the opening this Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: And being thereby invited to conſider of their Declaration of the Twenty ſixth of December laſt; they have with all Sobriety, Duty, and Affection, examined the grounds thereof, and do by me preſent unto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty their moſt hearty Thanks for the ſame, and humble Advice thereupon; both which, I do beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that you will vouchſafe me to deliver in their own words.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>May it pleaſe your moſt excellent Majeſty,</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Wee your Majeſties moſt Dutifull and Loyall Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes of the Houſe of Commons in Parliament Aſſembled, having with all fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and obedience conſidered of the ſeverall matters comprized in your Majeſties late Gratious Declaration of the 26 of Decemb. laſt, and your moſt gratious Speech at the beginning of this preſent Seſſion,</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Do in the firſt place for our ſelves, and in the names of all the Commons of England, render to your Sacred Majeſty, the Tribute of our moſt hearty Thanks for that infinite Grace and Goodneſs, wherewith your Majeſty hath been pleaſed to publiſh your Royall intentions, of adhering to your Act of Indempnity and Oblivion, by a conſtant and Religious obſervance of it. And our hearts are further enlarged in theſe returnes of Thanſgivings when we conſider your Majeſties moſt Princely, and Heroick Profeſſions of relying upon the Affections of your people, and abhorring all ſort of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary and arbitrary Rule. But above all wee can never enough remember, to the honour of your Majeſties Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and our unſpeakable Comfort, thoſe ſolemne and endearing Invitations of us your Majeſties Subjects
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40183:53"/> to prepare Lawes to be preſented to your Majeſty, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the growth and encreaſe of Popery; and withall to provide more Laws againſt Licentiouſneſs and impiety, at the ſame time declaring your own Reſolutions for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Act of Uniformity.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And it becomes us alwaies to acknowledge and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire your Majeſties Wiſdome in this your Declaration, whereby your Majeſty is pleaſed to reſolve, not only by ſumptuary Laws, but by your own Royall example of frugality, to reſtrain that exceſs in mens expences, which is grown ſo generall, and ſo exorbitant; and to direct our endeavours, to find out fit, &amp; proper Laws for advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Trade and Commerce.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>After all this we moſt humbly beſeech your Majeſty to believe, That it is with extream unwillingneſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy of heart, that we are brought to differ from any thing which your Majeſty hath thought fit to propoſe; And though we do no way doubt, but that the unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable diſtempers of mens ſpirits, and the many Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Conſpiracies which were carried on, during the late intervalls of Parliament, did reaſonably incline your Majeſty to endeavour by your declaration, to give ſome allay to thoſe ill humours, till the Parliament Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and the hopes of indulgence, if the Parliament ſhould conſent to it, eſpecially ſeeing the pretenders to this indulgence, did ſeem to make ſome titles to it, by vertue of your Majeſties Declaration from <hi>Breda.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, we your Majeſties moſt Dutifull and Loyall Subjects, who are now returned to ſerve in Parliament from thoſe ſeverall parts and places of your Kingdome, for which we are choſen, Do humbly offer to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties great VViſdome, That it is in no ſort adviſable,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40183:54"/> that there be any indulgence to ſuch perſons, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to diſſent from the Act of Uniformity, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion eſtabliſhed.</q>
            </p>
            <q>For theſe Reaſons,</q>
            <p>
               <q>We have conſidered the Nature of your Majeſties Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> and are humbly of Opinion, That your Majeſty ought not to be preſſed with it any farther,</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Becauſe it is not a promiſe in it ſelf, but only a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Declaration of your Majeſties Intentions, to doe what in you lay, and what a Parliament ſhould adviſe your Majeſty to doe; and no ſuch Advice was ever gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or thought fit to be offered; nor could it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe underſtood, becauſe there were Laws of Uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then in being, which could not be diſpenſed with, but by Act of Parliament.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>They who do pretend a right to that ſuppoſed promiſe, put the Right into the hands of their Repreſentatives, whom they choſe to ſerve for them in this Parliament, who have paſſed, and your Majeſty conſented to the Act of Uniformity. If any ſhall preſume to ſay, that a right to the benefit of this Declaration doth ſtill remain after this Act paſſed,</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>It tends to diſſolve the very Bonds of Goverment, and to ſuppoſe a diſability in your Majeſty and the Houſes of Parliament to make a Law contrary to any part of your Majeſties Declaration, though both Houſes ſhould adviſe your Majeſty to it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>We have alſo conſidered the nature of the Indulgence propoſed, with reference to thoſe conſequences, which muſt neceſſarily attend it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>It will eſtabliſh Schiſme by a Law, and make the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40183:54"/> whole Goverment of the Church precarious, and the Cenſures of it of no moment or Conſideration at all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>It will no way become the Gravity or Wiſdome of a Parliament, to paſſe a Law at one Seſſion for Uniformity, and at the next Seſſion (the Reaſons of Uniformity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſtill the ſame) to paſſe another Law to fruſtrate or weaken the execution of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>It will expoſe your Majeſty to the reſtleſſe importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every Sect or Opinion, and of every ſingle Perſon alſo, who ſhall preſume to diſſent from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>It will be a cauſe of increaſing Sects and Sectaries, whoſe numbers will weaken the true Proteſtant Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo far, that it will at leaſt be difficult for it, to defend it ſelf againſt them: And which is yet farther Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thoſe Numbers which by being troubleſome to the Government, find they can arrive to an Indulgence, will as their Numbers increaſe, be yet more troubleſome, that ſo at length they may arrive to a generall Toleration, which your Majeſty hath declared againſt, and in time ſome prevalent Sect, will at laſt contend for an eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which for ought can be foreſeen, may end in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>It is a thing altogether without precedent, and will take away all means of Convicting Recuſants, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Method and proceedings of the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Laſtly it is humbly conceived, that the Indulgence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd will be ſo far from tending to the peace of the Kingdom, that it is rather likely to occaſion great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance. And on the contrary; That the aſſerting of the Lawes, and the Religion eſtabliſh't, according to the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40183:55"/> 
                  <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Vniformity,</hi> is the moſt probable means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a ſettled Peace and Obedience throughout your Kingdome: Becauſe the variety of Profeſſions in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, when openly divulged, doth directly diſtinguiſh men into parties, and withall gives them opportunity to count their numbers; which conſidering the animoſities that out of a Religious Pride will be kept on foot by the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall factions, doth tend directly and inevitably to open diſturbance.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can your Majeſty have any Security, that the <q>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or Worſhip of the ſeverall Factions, which are all governed by a ſeverall Rule, ſhall be conſiſtent with the Peace of your Kingdome.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And if any perſons ſhall preſume to diſturb the peace of the Kingdome, We do in all humility declare, That we will for ever, and in all Occaſions, be ready with our utmoſt endeavour and Aſſiſtance, to adhere to and ſerve Your Majeſty according to our bounden Duty and Allegiance.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:40183:55"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have now given you my Authorities, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The private Teſtimonies of twenty emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Divines.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The publick Teſtimony of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Miniſters in the City of <hi>London</hi> (Synodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally) met at <hi>Sion</hi> Colledge.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Authority of that Wiſe, and Learned King <hi>James</hi> and his Privy Councill.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Votes and Reaſons of the Honourable Commons Aſſembled in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>All which I have deſignedly ranked in this method, that obſerving the <hi>order</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> and beginning <hi>ab imperfectiori,</hi> I might gradually aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to that which is more <hi>perfect;</hi> for ſuch I think the Reaſons of the <hi>Houſe</hi> will be found; (to him that dares attempt them) <hi>i. e.</hi> Impregnable and unanſwerable.</p>
            <p>I Know not how it fares with other men, (I am no judge of their <hi>honeſty</hi> or <hi>Knowledge</hi>) but I am ſure, as to me the premiſes have appeared ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40183:56"/> I ſhould think the world might ſuſpect either <hi>my Intellectualls,</hi> or <hi>Moralls,</hi> were I not <hi>thus</hi> apprehenſive of ſo convincing a Light.</p>
            <p>My Brethren, (that I may deal freely with you) I am perfectly amaz'd, and (I had almoſt ſaid) ſcandaliz'd; that <hi>men</hi> ſo eminent for <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> ſo noted for <hi>Piety,</hi> and (if we may beleive themſelves it being one of their grand Topickes for Indulgence) ſo conſiderable for <hi>Policy,</hi> I ſay, that theſe men ſhould ſo warmely concerne <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> for this <hi>Thing</hi> call'd <hi>Toleration,</hi> which (as I hope the premiſes have evinc'd) is not onely <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive</hi> both to Church &amp; State, but alſo (which prudent men would a little conſider) ſo direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>contrary</hi> to their former <hi>Principles</hi> &amp; <hi>Practices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am very unwilling to make any unpleaſing Reflections, but 'tis the Language of the world (and I am not yet inſtructed to confute it) that it is not a <hi>Toleration,</hi> (however pretended, as the moſt advantageous method, that can at <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> be employ'd) but a <hi>Reformation,</hi> (that is, (as ſad experience hath explained it) a totall <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation</hi> of what ever is contrary to their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and deſignes) that each different <hi>Partie</hi> endeavours to eſtabliſh.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:40183:56"/>
            <p>Now that this may not be rejected as a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering <hi>deſigne,</hi> onely to make you odious to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> (as is commonly objected) there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Reaſons (at leaſt ſtrong conjectures) that ſeeme highly to enforce the formentioned <hi>Charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> am willing to conclude; and ſhall <hi>therefore</hi> give you my notions in <hi>groſſe,</hi> leaving the Analy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis to your acuter Judgements.</p>
            <p>There are you know ſuch things in the world, as a <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of ſome one Forme of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a <hi>Solemne League and Covenant;</hi> both which as being directly contrary to your pretended <hi>Toleration,</hi> (had I but the leyſure or ability to improve them) might eaſily be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into Volume of Arguments.</p>
            <p>But leaving this performance (if occaſion ſhall require) to the management of ſome abler Pen, permit me very calmely to beg your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> to this following Propoſall.</p>
            <p>Were <hi>you</hi> in the ſame Condition, (<hi>i. e,</hi>) did <hi>you</hi> enjoy the ſame encourageing Circumſtances, that your Adverſaries, the true Sons of the Church of England (through Gods great mercy and the Indulgence of a gratious <hi>Prince</hi>) are at preſent favoured with; <hi>then</hi> lay your hands upon
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40183:57"/> your breaſts, and tell me, as in the Preſence of the great God that ſhall judge the world; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would you then indulge either Perſon or Parties, that ſhould diſſent from your eſtabliſhed Diſcipline, be it <hi>Preſbyterian,</hi> or <hi>Independent,</hi> or any other whatſoever: (<hi>e. g.</hi>) Whether would you then permit <hi>that Miniſter</hi> to preach publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſhould <hi>read the Service of our Church, weare a Surpliſse, uſe the Croſſe in Baptiſme, Kneel at the Sacrament,</hi> &amp;c: <hi>and not</hi> onely ſo, but the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of whoſe endeavours ſhould be employ'd in perſwading others to the like practices, telling them that the contrary (by you obſerved) was irreverent and undecent, and therefore of all good Chriſtians to be loath'd and abhorr'd, I ſay tell me <hi>plainly;</hi> Is it fit to grant a <hi>Toleration</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> to ſuch a Perſon or no? if not, then (even your ſelves being judges) neither is it fit to <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> you, ſince <hi>your</hi> Principles and Practices are as diſtant from <hi>his</hi> (I mean the true Son's of the Church of England) as his from <hi>yours,</hi> as deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to his, as his to yours: and <hi>it is unreaſonable</hi> (ſays the defender of the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters Letter to the Aſſembly) <hi>that Independents ſhould deſire that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ant. Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. p. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Toleration from Preſbyters, which they would not give
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40183:57"/> to Presbyters;</hi> ſo ſay I, it is unreaſonable that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, Presbyters, or any other Sect ſhould deſire that Toleration from Epiſcopacy, which they would not grant to Epiſcopacy. <hi>For with what face can I deſire a courteſie from him, to whom I do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly profeſſe, I would deny the ſame Courteſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now if you take the other member of the <hi>Contradiction,</hi> and ſay, <hi>you would tolerate the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd Perſon,</hi> ſuppoſeing him otherwiſe of a quiet, and peacable temper; let me then deſire you further to reſolve me. <hi>Are you perswaded, That the Church of England requires any thing Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as the condition of her Communion or not?</hi> if you ſay, <hi>ſhee does not</hi> (I am no little troubled to mention it, but theres no evaſion) I muſt plainly tell you, you are no better then downright Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maticks; for <hi>Schiſme</hi> in the proper notion of it is nothing <hi>elſe,</hi> but a <hi>cauſeles Separation from that part of the viſible Church of which we were members:</hi> now there is no ſufficient cauſe for ſuch <hi>Separation</hi> but <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs there be ſomething which is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as the Condition of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, it appears to me to be Schiſme to withdraw our ſelves.</hi> Def: of Propoſ. p. 91.</note> 
               <hi>Sin;</hi> it being the judgement of our beſt writers upon that Controverſie, that nothing else could warrant our Separation from <hi>Rome</hi> but this; that ſhe required as Conditions of her Communion ſomewhat in <hi>fide</hi> erroneous, or in <hi>facto</hi> impious.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:40183:58"/>
            <p>But if you are perſwaded (and ſome of you have declared it) <hi>that ſhe does require ſomething which is ſinfull, as the Condition of her Communion,</hi> then the Caſe is cleare; the Make falls of; and I have finiſhed my Taske; for, ſince all <hi>Sin</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly the object, not only of our hatred and <hi>averſation,</hi> but alſo of totall extirpation (it being every ones duty not only to avoid Sin himſelfe, but (by all lawfull waies and methods) to hinder its Commiſſion in others) I ſhall humbly leave it to his moſt ſacred <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and the Wiſdome of the <hi>Parliament</hi> to Conſider;</p>
            <p>VVhether it be either <hi>Religion,</hi> or <hi>Policie</hi> to tolerate thoſe Perſons, or Parties, which are perſwaded in their Conſciences, that it is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie incumbent Dutie, not onely to hate and deteſt, but alſo (by all thoſe waies and methods which they themſelves ſhall think lawfull) to weaken, alter, &amp; extirpate the ſettled Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Church?</hi> the which Alteration, what influence it may have upon the <hi>State,</hi> and how Deſtructive it may prove to his Majeſties Crown and Kingdomes, (I hope it is no breach of the Act of Oblivion to tell <hi>you</hi>) the experience of late <hi>years</hi> hath ſuggeſted a very fatall conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:40183:58"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS</head>
            <list>
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Author no ſcoffer at Religion. p.</hi> 2.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Occaſion of this work.</hi> 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Author diſſatisfied about Toleration.</hi> 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Toleration is unpracticable.</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The petitioners for Tol: ſcarce intelligible in their Propoſals.</hi> 9.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Teſtimonies of twenty eminent Divines againſt Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> 11.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Particularly.</head>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Aſh.</hi> 50.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Corn: Burgeſs.</hi> 15.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> 37.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Calamy.</hi> 33.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Caſe.</hi> 28.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Cranford</hi> 51.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Edwards.</hi> 53.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Good.</hi> 23.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hardwick.</hi> 26.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Horton.</hi> 39.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hughes.</hi> 32.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lightfoot.</hi> 31.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Newcomen</hi> 42.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Reyner.</hi> 28.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Salwey.</hi> 27.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Seaman.</hi> 41.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thorowgood.</hi> 24.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Vines.</hi> 49.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Ward,</hi> 19.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Watſon,</hi> 31.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Letter of the Presbyterian Miniſters in the City of London to the Aſſembly, againſt Toleration.</hi> 61.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Judgement of King</hi> James <hi>and his Privy Councill againſt Toleration.</hi> 71.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Votes and Reaſons of this preſent Parliament againſt Toleration.</hi> 75.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>A ſerious reflection upon the Premiſes.</hi> 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>'Tis not Tol: but Reformation that N. C. intend.</hi> 82.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Reaſons which cauſed the Author ſo to think.</hi> 83.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Propoſall which N. C. are deſired to reſolve. ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>N. C. are Schiſmaticks.</hi> 85.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A very humble Addreſs to his Majeſty and the Parliament.</hi> 86</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
